<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home</title>
    <link>https://www.musclehacking.com</link>
    <description>An evidence based approach to fitness and nutrition. Free articles and guides on how to use intermittent fasting to gain muscle, lose fat, and improve your memory and focus.</description>
    <atom:link href="https://www.musclehacking.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      <item>
        <title>What is the Best Type of Protein Powder for Building Muscle?</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<p><strong>You’ve made up your mind</strong>. </p>
<p>You’re going to supplement your diet with more protein. Fantastic.</p>
<p>But as you browse online you are attacked by an endless list of protein powders. </p>
<p>Whey protein. Casein protein. Pea protein. Rice protein. Apple-pie protein. </p>
<p>Okay, the last one isn’t a real thing (<em>yet</em>). But there is definitely no shortage of exotically named protein supplements. </p>
<p>So which type of protein powder is the most effective for gaining muscle? </p>
<h3>What Matters In Your Protein Powder</h3><p>There are four key areas to consider when evaluating a protein powder: </p>
<ol class="ol-pad">
<li class="li-pad"><a href="#protein-percentage" title='Protein Percentage'><strong>Protein Percentage</strong></a>
</li>
<li class="li-pad"><a href="#amino-acid" title='Amino Acid Content'><strong>Amino Acid Content</strong></a>
</li>
<li class="li-pad"><a href="#speed" title='Speed Of Digestion'><strong>Speed Of Digestion</strong></a>
</li>
<li class="li-pad"><a href="#price-and-taste" title='Price And Taste'><strong>Price And Taste</strong></a>
</li>
</ol>

<p>The sections below provide an overview of each area.</p>
<p>If you want to skip to the comparison, you can go straight to the <a href="#table" title='Protein Comparison Table'><strong>Protein Comparison Table</strong></a>. </p>
<h4 id="protein-percentage">Protein Percentage</h4>

<p>This is the protein percentage by calorie.  </p>
<p>For example, this nutrition label: </p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new15">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/protein-label.jpg" alt="Nutrition information label of a protein powder.">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Example protein powder nutrition label. </p>


<p>Shows that the protein powder has approximately 81% protein by calories. That’s calculated via:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>78.9 protein &times; 4 kcal per g protein &ap; 316 kcal</p>
<p>316 kcal / 390 kcal &times; 100 = 81% </p>
</blockquote>
<p>Different protein powders have very different levels of protein content. From as low as 60% protein to above 95% protein, the range is huge.</p>
<p>The variation in protein percentage depends on two factors:</p>
<ul id="ul-nm1"class="ol-pad">
<li class="li-pad"><a id="no-ul1" href="#type-of-protein" title='Different Types Of Protein'>The Type Of Protein</a>
</li>
<li class="li-pad"><a id="no-ul2" href="#brand-of-protein" title='Different Brands Of Protein'>The Brand Of Protein</a>
</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="type-of-protein">The Type Of Protein</h5>

<p>The type of protein means either a <strong><em>completely different source of protein</em></strong> or the <strong><em>same source but refined to a different extent</em></strong>.</p>
<p>An example of a <strong><em>completely different source</em></strong> is whey protein vs wheat protein. Whey protein is derived from milk. Wheat protein is derived from wheat. These are fundamentally different sources of protein.</p>
<p>The process of extracting protein from milk is different from the process of extracting protein from wheat. Part of the final cost of the protein powder will depend on how costly it is to refine and isolate the protein from the source.</p>
<p><strong>More refinement &#8594; More costly.</strong></p>
<p>There is a point where it is no longer economical to further refine a protein source to get a higher percentage yield of protein. This is reflected in the final protein content of different sources of protein.</p>
<p>It’s why you see rice and hemp protein (generally) having lower protein content than whey protein. Extracting whey protein from milk is cheaper than extracting the equivalent amount of protein from rice or hemp. </p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new2">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/what-is-hemp-protein.jpg" alt="Pot of hemp seeds with a hemp leaf placed on top.">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Hemp protein is made from hemp seeds. Yes – weed. </p>

<p>An example of the <strong><em>same source refined to a different extent</em></strong> is Whey Protein Isolate vs Whey Protein Concentrate. </p>
<p>Both Whey Protein Isolate (WPI) and Whey Protein Concentrate (WPC) are derived from milk. The source of protein is the same. </p>
<p>The difference here is the refinement process. You get whey protein by pushing milk through a filter, removing the curd (<em>that’s your casein protein</em>). Let the whey protein dry, and you’re left with your WPC. </p>
<p>If you keep processing and refining your WPC – removing more lactose and fat – you get WPI. </p>
<p><strong><em>WPI is just a more refined version of WPC.</em></strong></p>
<p>As you would expect, removal of lactose and fat results in WPI having a higher protein content than WPC, regardless of the supplier.</p>
<h5 id="brand-of-protein">The Brand Of Protein</h5>

<p>The brand of a protein comes into play when you’re comparing the same protein from two different suppliers.</p>
<p>For example, <strong><em>Peter’s Protein</em></strong> and <strong><em>Steve’s Supplements</em></strong> both sell Whey Protein Concentrate (WPC).</p>
<p>But Peter’s WPC has 85% protein, while Steve’s WPC only has 70% protein.</p>
<p>This is a common occurrence: there is a large variation in protein content between suppliers, even for the same type of protein powder.</p>
<p>This variation depends on the amount of filler and flavouring they put into the protein, as well as their refinement process. </p>
<p><strong>This can vary a lot</strong>. If you’ve compared the nutrition label of a few brands of WPC, you’ll know exactly what I mean.</p>
<p>This is why it’s important to look deeper than just the type of protein. The brand matters too – not all suppliers were made equal.</p>
<h4 id="amino-acid">Amino Acid Content</h4>

<p>Amino acids are the building blocks of protein. They come in two forms: </p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Unessential Amino Acids</strong> are amino acids naturally made by your body. 11 of the 20 amino acids are “<em>unessential</em>”.</li>
<li><strong>Essential Amino Acids (EAAs)</strong> are amino acids that aren’t made by your body, which instead need to be consumed as part of your diet. 9 of the 20 amino acids are “<em>essential</em>”.</li>
</ul>
<p>3 of those 9 EAAs are categorised as <em>Branched-Chain Amino Acids</em> – or BCAAs for short. <a href="#leucine" title='Studies on BCAA’s role in muscle building' target='_blank'>These have been found</a> to be particularly important for building muscle.</p>
<p><strong>Leucine</strong> is the most powerful BCAA, and the single most important nutrient for building muscle. There is a <a href="#leucine" title='Studies on leucine’s role in muscle building' target='_blank'>lot of research</a> demonstrating the importance of leucine in muscle building. </p>
<p>By definition, EAAs need to be consumed as part of your diet. And if there were any part of your diet you would expect to get your EAAs, it would be your protein supplements. </p>
<p>Here’s the thing: <strong>the <em>type</em> and <em>amount</em> of amino acids will depend on the type of protein.</strong></p>
<p>Not all protein was made equal. 10g of protein from eggs is going to have a completely different amino acid composition than 10g of protein from spinach.</p>
<p>As a visual example, the graph below compares the EAA content of whey protein vs rice protein. The data was taken from <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23782948" target='_blank' title='The Effects of 8 Weeks of Whey or Rice Protein Supplementation on Body Composition and Exercise Performance'>this study</a> comparing whey protein to rice protein.</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--55">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/whey-protein-vs-rice-protein.png" alt="Graph comparing the essential amino acid content of whey protein versus rice protein.">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Essential Amino Acid Composition of Whey Protein vs Rice Protein </p>

<p>Whey protein is higher in all three BCAAs, and overall has a higher EAA content for 6 of the 9 EAAs.</p>
<p>4 of these 6 EAAs – Isoleucine, Leucine, Lysine, and Threonine – are <em>a lot</em> higher in whey protein than they are in rice protein.</p>
<p>This translates to more EAA bang for your buck per gram of whey protein versus rice protein. The source of the protein makes a difference.</p>
<p>Hence we have to consider more than just the pure protein content of a protein powder. The amino acid composition – particularly the BCAA and leucine content – should also be taken into account.</p>
<h4 id="speed">Speed Of Digestion</h4>

<p>This is how long it takes for your protein to be digested. </p>
<p>An example of this is whey protein vs casein protein. Both of these proteins are derived from milk – milk protein being 20% whey protein and 80% casein protein. </p>
<p><strong><em>Whey protein</em></strong> is digested rapidly – reaching peaking amino acid levels after an hour, and taking about 4 hours to fully digest.</p>
<p><strong><em>Casein protein</em></strong> takes longer – the amino acid levels don’t peak as high, but are sustained for over 7 hours. </p>
<p>This doesn’t matter as much as most supplement companies would have you believe.</p>
<p>This is because <strong><em>it’s a mistake to consider the consumption of your protein supplements in a vacuum</em></strong>. </p>
<p>It’s true that casein protein won’t pass through your body as quickly as whey protein. But this neglects the fact that you’ll have: </p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Protein flowing through your veins from other sources</strong></li>
<li><strong>Other food slowing the digestion of your protein</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>For instance, many recommend that you consume casein protein – as opposed to whey protein – before bed. The logic is to allow the protein to digest slowly while you sleep.</p>
<p>In a vacuum, this sounds reasonable. </p>
<p>But you don’t live in a vacuum – you had steak and veggies for dinner. Or a similar mixed meal of fats, carbohydrates, and protein. </p>
<p>So there will already be protein flowing through your body from that meal. This makes the speed of digestion a non-factor. </p>
<p>This is reflected in the literature, with the majority of <a href="#whey-vs-casein" title='Studies on whey protein versus casein protein' target='_blank'>studies finding no significant difference</a> between whey protein and casein protein’s ability to enhance body composition.</p>
<p>That means that the “<em>slow digesting</em>” nature of a protein isn’t an important factor of consideration.</p>
<p>Well then, what about the other side of the coin: <strong>digesting <em>really fast</em></strong>.</p>
<p><strong id="whey-hydrolysate">Whey hydrolysate</strong> jumps to mind as the fan-favourite example. Whey hydrolysate is taking whey protein refinement to the next level, breaking down some of the amino acid bonds by exposing them to heat, acids, or enzymes.</p>
<p>Effectively whey hydrolysate is whey protein that has been broken down into smaller molecules for quicker absorption. This pre-digestion makes hydrolysed proteins more rapidly absorbed than whey concentrates or isolates. </p>
<p>The story behind their benefit sounds believable: this <strong><em>lightning-fast digestion</em></strong> allows you to deliver a <strong><em>muscle-building dose</em></strong> of protein straight to your biceps post-workout. </p>
<p>Sounds sexy right?</p>
<p>Slight issue though – <strong>it doesn’t work like that</strong>. </p>
<p>For two main reasons: </p>
<ol class="ol-pad">
<li class="li-pad"><strong>The post-workout anabolic window has been <a class="anchor" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23360586" title="Nutrient timing revisited: is there a post-exercise anabolic window?" target="_blank">revealed to be irrelevant to most lifters.</a></strong>
</li>
<li class="li-pad"><strong>Whey hydrolysate has been shown to be <em>less effective</em> in building muscle.</strong>
</li>
</ol>


<p>That’s right. </p>
<p><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0958694613001787 " title="Hydrolysed whey protein reduces muscle damage markers in Brazilian elite soccer players compared with whey protein and maltodextrin. A twelve-week in-championship intervention" target="_blank">In a 2013 study</a>, athletes consumed either whey protein concentrate (WPC), whey protein hydrolysate (WPH), or pure sugar. </p>
<p>The scientists found that WPH decreased muscle damage more than either WPC or the sugar.</p>
<p>This sounds like something we would want, <strong>but it’s not</strong>. </p>
<p>Since muscle damage is actually necessary for muscle growth to occur, WPH had a <strong>negative effect</strong> on body composition. </p>
<p>The study found that <strong>WPH resulted in 65% less muscle gain than the WPC.</strong></p>
<p>And if that wasn’t bad enough: the WPH resulted in <strong>fat <em>gain</em> instead of fat <em>loss</em></strong>. The WPC and sugar didn’t. </p>
<p><strong><em>So the WPH was found to be more fattening than a shake of sugar.</em></strong></p>
<p>Don’t pay more for less. More research needs to be done on whey protein hydrolysate before anyone can promote it as “<em>superior</em>” for muscle building. For now, it’s all hype.</p>
<p>Overall this means that your protein’s speed of digestion – whether it be super fast or super slow – is not a good reason to pay more. </p>
<p>Hence the speed of digestion has not been included in the  <a href="#table" title='Protein Comparison Table'><strong>Protein Comparison Table</strong></a>.</p>
<h4 id="price-and-taste">Price And Taste</h4>

<p>If you have taste buds and any kind of budget, price and taste matter. In an ideal world they wouldn’t, but in our world they do.</p>
<p>Thankfully in the realm of protein powder, you don’t need to break the bank to afford effective protein supplements.</p>
<p>It’s often the opposite: many of the more expensive forms of protein are actually <strong>less effective</strong>.</p>
<p>This higher cost is typically the result of large advertising campaigns, and the ridiculous refinement processes required to extract the protein from this week’s trendy superfood.</p>
<p>So don’t make the mistake of thinking more expensive = more effective. It isn’t.</p>
<p><strong>Taste</strong> varies a lot depending on the <a href="#type-of-protein" title='Different Types Of Protein'><em><strong>type of protein</strong></em></a> and the <a href="#brand-of-protein" title='Different Brands Of Protein'><em><strong>brand of protein</strong></em></a>.</p>
<p>For the <strong><em>type of protein</em></strong>, milk-derived protein powders tend to taste the best. </p>
<p>But you’ll see the largest variation in taste between different <strong><em>brands of protein</em></strong>. </p>
<p>The quality and quantity of sweetener(s) supplement companies use result in very different tasting protein. Even when they’re the exact same type of protein. </p>
<p>Taste-wise, the brand makes all the difference.</p>
<p>So before you order 10kg of protein powder from your chosen supplier, make sure you check the reviews online. If the company sells sample packs, order one of those first before you commit to a bulk purchase.</p>
<h3 id="table">Protein Comparison Table</h3>

<p>The table below rates each protein powder on five metrics: BCAA content, leucine content, protein content, price, and taste.</p>
<p>References are <a href="#references" title='References'>included below</a>.</p>
<div class="table-responsive">
  <table id="ps-table" class="table">
    <thead>
      <tr id="ps-row">
        <th id="ps-col1"scope="col">Protein Source</th>
        <th scope="col" style="width: 14%;">BCAA</th>
        <th scope="col" style="width: 14%;">Leucine</th>
        <th scope="col" style="width: 14%;">Protein</th>
        <th scope="col" style="width: 14%;">Price</th>
        <th id="ps-col6" scope="col">Taste</th>
      </trps-table>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr id="whey" class="b-hover">
        <td id=""class="r-alg"> Whey Concentrate &dagger;
        </td>
        <td class="gre2"> 26%
        </td>
        <td class="gre2"> 14%
        </td>
        <td class="ye1"> 75%+
        </td>
        <td class="gre1"> Low
        </td>
        <td class="gre2 end"> Very good
      </tr>
      <tr class="b-hover">
        </td>
        <td id=""class="r-alg"> Whey Isolate
        </td>
        <td class="gre2"> 26%
        </td>
        <td class="gre2"> 14%
        </td>
        <td class="gre2"> 90%+
        </td>
        <td class="ye1"> Medium
        </td>
        <td class="gre1 end"> Good
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr class="b-hover">
        <td id=""class="r-alg"> Whey Hydrolysateˆ 
        </td>
        <td class="gre2"> 26%
        </td>
        <td class="gre2"> 14%
        </td>
        <td class="gre2"> 94%+
        </td>
        <td class="re1"> High
        </td>
        <td class="ye1 end"> Medium
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr class="b-hover">
        <td class="r-alg"> Casein
        </td>
        <td class="gre1"> 21%
        </td>
        <td class="ye1"> 9%
        </td>
        <td class="gre1"> 85%+
        </td>
        <td class="ye1"> Medium
        </td>
        <td class="gre1 end"> Good
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr class="b-hover">
        <td id=""class="r-alg"> Milk &#9824; 
        </td>
        <td class="gre1"> 21%
        </td>
        <td class="ye1"> 10%
        </td>
        <td class="gre1"> 85%+
        </td>
        <td class="ye1"> Medium
        </td>
        <td class="gre1 end"> Good
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr class="b-hover">
        <td id=""class="r-alg"> Egg
        </td>
        <td class="gre1"> 20%
        </td>
        <td class="ye1"> 8.5%
        </td>
        <td class="gre1"> 90%+
        </td>
        <td class="re1"> High
        </td>
        <td class="re1 end"> Poor
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr class="b-hover">
        <td id=""class="r-alg"> Beef Protein Isolate
        </td>
        <td class="re2"> 8%
        </td>
        <td class="re2"> 3%
        </td>
        <td class="gre2"> 95%+
        </td>
        <td class="re1"> High
        </td>
        <td class="re1 end"> Poor
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr class="b-hover">
        <td id=""class="r-alg"> Soy Isolate
        </td>
        <td class="ye1"> 18%
        </td>
        <td class="re1"> 8%
        </td>
        <td class="gre1"> 85%+
        </td>
        <td class="gre1"> Low
        </td>
        <td class="ye1 end"> Medium
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr class="b-hover">
        <td id=""class="r-alg"> Wheat
        </td>
        <td class="re1"> 15%
        </td>
        <td class="re1"> 7%
        </td>
        <td class="gre2"> 94%+
        </td>
        <td class="re1"> High
        </td>
        <td class="ye1 end"> Medium
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr class="b-hover">
        <td id=""class="r-alg"> Pea
        </td>
        <td class="ye1"> 18%
        </td>
        <td class="ye1"> 8.5%
        </td>
        <td class="ye1"> 80%+
        </td>
        <td class="gre1"> Low
        </td>
        <td class="ye1 end"> Medium
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr class="b-hover">
        <td id=""class="r-alg"> Rice
        </td>
        <td class="ye1"> 18%
        </td>
        <td class="re1"> 8%
        </td>
        <td class="re1"> 60%+
        </td>
        <td class="gre1"> Low
        </td>
        <td class="re1 end"> Poor
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr class="b-hover">
        <td id=""class="r-alg"> Hemp
        </td>
        <td class="re1"> 16%
        </td>
        <td class="re1"> 7%
        </td>
        <td class="re1"> 60%+
        </td>
        <td class="re1"> High
        </td>
        <td class="ye1 end"> Medium
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</div>

<p><em>Note: Speed of digestion has been omitted as its effect is negligible (<a href="#speed" title='Speed of Digestion'>as discussed</a>). Remember that Price and Taste are referring to the protein in powder form. Normal eggs are cheap and delicious – but egg protein powder is expensive and gross.</em></p>
<p>&dagger; There is a large variation in the protein percentage of Whey Concentrate, although it is typically above 75%.</p>
<p>&#9824; Milk protein is 80% casein protein and 20% whey protein.</p>
<p>&circ; The incredibly fast digestion of Whey Hydrolysate may negatively impact muscle building. See discussion in <a href="#whey-hydrolysate" title='Whey hydrolysate vs whey isolate'>Speed Of Digestion</a>.</p>
<p>That’s it for this post. If you found this useful, don’t forget to share it on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=https://musclehacking.com/blog/best-protein-for-building-muscle" target="_blank" title='Share on Facebook'>Facebook</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=Interesting+read:%20https://musclehacking.com/blog/best-protein-for-building-muscle%20via%20@musclehacking" target="_blank" title='Share on Twitter'>Twitter</a>.</p>
<h3 id="notes">Notes for Nerds</h3>
<h5 id="">On BCAA and Leucine Content</h5>

<p>Different studies report slightly different values for the amino acid profile of various proteins. Regardless, the relative differences between proteins (e.g. leucine in whey protein vs leucine in rice protein) remain largely the same.</p>
<h5 id="">On Slow vs Fast Digesting Protein</h5>

<p>While there are a few studies that show statistically significant differences in muscle gain when comparing slow versus fast digesting protein, these are the exception, not the rule. </p>
<p>These studies use unrealistic experimental conditions, such as fasting for 12+ hours before the workout or consuming <em>only</em> the protein supplement post-workout.</p>
<p>Many of these studies are funded by industries that have a vested interest in there being a difference. Even under these ideal conditions for differences to reveal themselves, the majority of studies show no difference. </p>
<p>Hence the onus is on further research to strengthen the argument that the <a href="#speed" title='Speed Of Digestion'>speed of digestion</a> of a protein has a practical application in muscle building for the average gym-goer.</p>
<p>Note that by ‘average’ I mean people who <strong><em>aren’t</em></strong> working out 2+ times per day or fasting for long periods of time pre or post workout.</p>
<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<h5 id="leucine">Importance Of Leucine And BCAAs</h5>

<ol class="ref-list">
<li class="ref">B. Pennings, B. Groen, A. de Lange, A. P. Gijsen, A. H. Zorenc, J. M. G. Senden, and L. J. C. van Loon, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22338070" target="_blank">Amino acid absorption and subsequent muscle protein accretion following graded intakes of whey protein in elderly men</a>,” <em>AJP: Endocrinology and Metabolism</em>, vol. 302, pp. E992–E999, apr 2012.</li>
<li class="ref"> T. A. Churchward-Venne, N. A. Burd, C. J. Mitchell, D. W. West, A. Philp, G. R. Marcotte, S. K. Baker, K. Baar, and S. M. Phillips, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22451437" target="_blank">Supplementation of a suboptimal protein dose with leucine or essential amino acids: Effects on myofibrillar protein synthesis at rest and following resistance exercise in men</a>,” <em>Journal of Physiology</em>, vol. 590, no. 11, pp. 2751–2765, 2012.</li>
<li class="ref"> M. G. Buse and S. S. Reid, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC301988/" target="_blank">Leucine. A possible regulator of protein turnover in 
muscle</a>,” <em>Journal of Clinical Investigation</em>, vol. 56, pp. 1250–1261, nov 1975.</li>
<li class="ref"> S. O. Hong and D. K. Layman, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/6737085" target="_blank">Effects of leucine on in vitro protein synthesis and degradation in rat skeletal muscles.</a>,” <em>The Journal of Nutrition</em>, vol. 114, pp. 1204–12, jul 1984.</li> 
<li class="ref"> J. C. Anthony, T. G. Anthony, S. R. Kimball, and L. S. Jefferson, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11238774" target="_blank">Signaling Pathways Involved in Translational Control of Protein Synthesis in Skeletal Muscle by Leucine</a>,” <em>The Journal of Nutrition</em>, vol. 131, pp. 856S–860S, apr 2001.</li> 
<li class="ref"> X. J. Zhang, D. L. Chinkes, and R. R. Wolfe, “<a href="https://academic.oup.com/jn/article/134/12/3313/4688553" target="_blank">Leucine supplementation has an anabolic effect on proteins in rabbit skin wound and muscle</a>,” <em>The Journal of Nutrition</em>, vol. 134, pp. 3313–3318, dec 2004.</li> 
<li class="ref"> D. J. Wilkinson, S. S. Bukhari, B. E. Phillips, M. C. Limb, J. Cegielski, M. S. Brook, D. Rankin, W. K. Mitchell, H. Kobayashi, J. P. Williams, J. Lund, P. L. Greenhaff, K. Smith, and P. J. Atherton, “<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0261561417313407" target="_blank">Effects of leucine-enriched essential amino acid and whey protein bolus dosing upon skeletal muscle protein synthesis at rest and after exercise in older women</a>,” <em>Clinical Nutrition</em>, pp. 1–11, 2017.</li> 
<li class="ref"> P. J. Atherton, V. Kumar, A. L. Selby, D. Rankin, W. Hildebrandt, B. E. Phillips, J. P. Williams, N. Hiscock, and K. Smith, “<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0261561416300711" target="_blank">Enriching a protein drink with leucine augments muscle protein synthesis after resistance exercise in young and older men</a>,” <em>Clinical Nutrition</em>, vol. 36, no. 3, pp. 888–895, 2017.</li> 
<li class="ref"> J. M. Dickinson, D. M. Gundermann, D. K. Walker, P. T. Reidy, M. S. Borack, M. J. Drum, M. Arora, E. Volpi, and B. B. Rasmussen, “<a href="https://academic.oup.com/jn/article/144/11/1694/4644326" target="_blank">Leucine-Enriched Amino Acid Ingestion after Resistance Exercise Prolongs Myofibrillar Protein Synthesis and Amino Acid Transporter Expression in Older Men 1 - 3</a>,” <em>The Journal of Nutrition</em>, vol. 144, pp. 1694–1702, 2014.</li>  
<li class="ref"> P. J. Atherton, K. Smith, T. Etheridge, D. Rankin, and M. J. Rennie, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19882215" target="_blank">Distinct anabolic signalling responses to amino acids in C2C12 skeletal muscle cells</a>,” <em>Amino Acids</em>, vol. 38, no. 5, pp. 1533–1539, 2010.</li>  
<li class="ref"> J. C. Anthony, T. G. Anthony, and D. K. Layman, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10356072" target="_blank">Leucine supplementation enhances skeletal muscle recovery in rats following exercise.</a>,” <em>The Journal of Nutrition</em>, vol. 129, pp. 1102–6, jun 1999.</li>  
<li class="ref"> R. Koopman, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15562251" target="_blank">Combined ingestion of protein and free leucine with carbohydrate increases postexercise muscle protein synthesis in vivo in male subjects</a>,” <em>AJP: Endocrinology and Metabolism</em>, vol. 288, pp. E645–E653, apr 2004.</li>  
<li class="ref"> Y. C. Luiking, N. E. Deutz, R. G. Memelink, S. Verlaan, and R. R. Wolfe, “<a href="https://nutritionj.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1475-2891-13-9" target="_blank">Postprandial muscle protein synthesis is higher after a high whey protein, leucine-enriched supplement than after a dairy-like product in healthy older people: A randomized controlled trial</a>,” <em>Nutrition Journal</em>, vol. 13, p. 9, dec 2014.</li>  
<li class="ref"> S. R. Kimball and L. S. Jefferson, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11122558" target="_blank">Regulation of protein synthesis by branched-chain amino acids.</a>,” <em>Current Opinion in Clinical Nutrition and Metabolic Care</em>, vol. 4, pp. 39–43, jan 2001.</li>  
<li class="ref"> J. B. Li and L. S. Jefferson, “<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0304416578901034" target="_blank">Influence of amino acid availability on protein turnover in perfused skeletal muscle</a>,” <em>Biochemica et Biophysica Acta</em>, vol. 544, pp. 351–359, 1978.</li> 
<li class="ref"> B. Cambell, R. B. Kreider, T. Ziegenfuss, P. L. Bounty, M. Roberts, D. Burke,
J. Landis, H. Lopez, and J. Antonio, “<a href="https://jissn.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1550-2783-4-8" target="_blank">International Society of Sports Nutrition position stand: protein and exercise</a>,” <em>Journal of International Society of Sports Nutrition</em>, vol. 4, no. 23, pp. 1–5, 2007.</li>  
<li class="ref"> D. J. Millward, D. K. Layman, D. Tomé, and G. Schaafsma, “<a href="https://academic.oup.com/ajcn/article/87/5/1576S/4650447" target="_blank">Protein quality assessment: impact of expanding understanding of protein and amino acid needs for optimal health</a>,” <em>The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition</em>, vol. 87, pp. 1576–81, may 2008.</li> 
</ol>

<h5 id="whey-vs-casein">Whey Protein vs Casein Protein</h5>

<ol class="ref-list" start="18">
<li class="ref"> S. L. Urbina, A. White, J. Shaw, C. Wilborn, and B. Brabham, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3238160/" target="_blank">The effects of post-exercise whey vs. casein protein ingestion on muscular strength, muscular endurance, and body composition in older women (50-70 years of age)</a>,” <em>Journal of the International Society of Sports Nutrition</em>, vol. 8, no. Suppl 1, p. P27, 2011.</li>  
<li class="ref"> C. D. Wilborn, L. W. Taylor, J. Outlaw, L. Williams, B. Campbell, C. A. Foster,
A. Smith-Ryan, S. Urbina, and S. Hayward, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3761774/" target="_blank">The effects of pre- and post-exercise whey vs. casein protein consumption on body composition and performance measures in collegiate female athletes</a>,” <em>Journal of Sports Science and Medicine</em>, vol. 12, no. 1, pp. 74–79, 2013.</li>  
</ol>
<h5 id="protein-timing">Protein Timing</h5>

<ol class="ref-list" start="20">
<li class="ref">
A. A. Aragon and B. J. Schoenfeld, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23360586" target="_blank">Nutrient timing revisited: Is there a post-exercise anabolic window?</a>,” <em>Journal of the International Society of Sports Nutrition</em>, vol. 10, 2013.</li>  
</ol>
<h5 id="hydrolysed-whey">Hydrolysed Whey</h5>

<ol class="ref-list" start="21">
<li class="ref">P. C. Lollo, J. Amaya-Farfan, I. C. Faria, J. V. Salgado, M. P. Chacon-Mikahil, A. G. Cruz, C. A. Oliveira, P. C. Montagner, and M. Arruda, “<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0958694613001787" target="_blank">Hydrolysed whey protein reduces muscle damage markers in Brazilian elite soccer players compared with whey protein and maltodextrin. A twelve-week in-championship intervention</a>,” <em>International Dairy Journal</em>, vol. 34, no. 1, pp. 19–24, 2014.</li>  
<li class="ref">C. M. Lockwood, M. D. Roberts, V. J. Dalbo, A. E. Smith-Ryan, K. L. Kendall, J. R. Moon, and J. R. Stout, “<a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/07315724.2016.1140094?src=recsys" target="_blank">Effects of Hydrolyzed Whey versus Other Whey Protein Supplements on the Physiological Response to 8 Weeks of Resistance Exercise in College-Aged Males</a>,” <em>Journal of the American College of Nutrition</em>, vol. 36, no. 1, pp. 16–27, 2017.</li>  
</ol>
<h5 id="#bcaa-leucine-content">BCAA And Leucine Content</h5>

<ol class="ref-list" start="23">
<li class="ref"> D. K. Layman and J. I. Baum, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15051856" target="_blank">Dietary protein impact on glycemic control during weight loss.</a>,” <em>The Journal of Nutrition</em>, vol. 134, pp. 968S–73S, oct 2004.</li>  
<li class="ref">C. C. Almeida, T. S. Alvares, M. P. Costa, and C. A. Conte-Junior, “<a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.3109/19390211.2015.1036187?scroll=top&needAccess=true" target="_blank">Protein and Amino Acid Profiles of Different Whey Protein Supplements</a>,” <em>Journal of Dietary Supplements</em>, vol. 13, no. 3, pp. 313–323, 2016.</li>  
<li class="ref">J. Overduin, L. Guérin-Deremaux, D. Wils, and T. T. Lambers, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4400298/" target="_blank">NUTRALYS® pea protein: Characterization of in vitro gastric digestion and in vivo gastrointestinal peptide responses relevant to satiety</a>,” <em>Food and Nutrition Research</em>, vol. 59, pp. 1–9, 2015.</li>  
<li class="ref">V. R. Young and P. L. Pellett, “<a href="https://academic.oup.com/ajcn/article-abstract/59/5/1203S/4732587?redirectedFrom=fulltext" target="_blank">Plant proteins in relation to human protein and amino acid nutrition</a>,” in <em>The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition</em>, vol. 59, pp. 1203S–1212S, Oxford University Press, may 1994.</li>  
<li class="ref">P. E. Miller, D. D. Alexander, and V. Perez, “<a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/07315724.2013.875365?src=recsys" target="_blank">Effects of Whey Protein and Resistance Exercise on Body Composition: A Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials</a>,” <em>Journal of the American College of Nutrition</em>, vol. 33, no. 2, pp. 163–175, 2014.</li> 
<li class="ref">C. V. Morr and E. Y. Ha, “<a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/10408399309527643?src=recsys" target="_blank">Whey Protein Concentrates and Isolates: Processing and Functional Properties</a>,” <em>Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition</em>, vol. 33, pp. 431–476, jan 1993.</li>  
<li class="ref">S. Sindayikengera and W. Xia, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1363751/" target="_blank">Nutritional evaluation of caseins and whey proteins and their hydrolysates from Protamex</a>,” <em>Journal of Zhejiang University Science B</em>, vol. 7, no. 2, pp. 90–98, 2006.</li>  
<li class="ref">S. Rafiq, N. Huma, I. Pasha, A. Sameen, O. Mukhtar, and M. I. Khan, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4932579/" target="_blank">Chemical composition, nitrogen fractions and amino acids profile of milk from different animal species</a>,” <em>Asian-Australasian Journal of Animal Sciences</em>, vol. 29, no. 7, pp. 1022–1028, 2016.</li>  
<li class="ref">W. G. Gordon, W. F. Semmett, and M. Bender, “<a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/ja01103a048" target="_blank">Amino Acid Composition of γ-Casein</a>,” <em>Journal of the American Chemical Society</em>, vol. 75, no. 3, pp. 1678–1679, 1953.</li>  
<li class="ref">B. H. Lauer and B. E. Baker, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/13923" target="_blank">Amino acid composition of casein isolated from the milks of different species.</a>,” 1977.</li> 
<li class="ref">N. Ganguli, R. Prabhakaran, and K. Iya, “<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S002203026488574X" target="_blank">Composition of the Caseins of Buffalo and Cow Milk</a>,” <em>Journal of Dairy Science</em>, vol. 47, no. 1, pp. 13–18, 1964.</li> 
<li class="ref">B. Y. W. G. Gordon and W. F. Semmett, “<a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/ja01178a006" target="_blank">Amino Acid Composition of α-Casein and β-Casein</a>,” <em>Journal of the American Chemical Society</em>, vol. V, no. 3, 1949.</li> 
<li class="ref">D. Kalman, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5302255/" target="_blank">Amino Acid Composition of an Organic Brown Rice Protein Concentrate and Isolate Compared to Soy and Whey Concentrates and Isolates</a>,” <em>Foods</em>, vol. 3, no. 3, pp. 394–402, 2014.</li> 
<li class="ref">J. M. Joy, R. P. Lowery, J. M. Wilson, M. Purpura, E. O. De Souza, S. M. Wilson, D. S. Kalman, J. E. Dudeck, and R. Jäger, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23782948" target="_blank">The effects of 8 weeks of whey or rice protein supplementation on body composition and exercise performance</a>,” <em>Nutrition Journal</em>, vol. 12, no. 1, pp. 1–7, 2013.</li> 
<li class="ref">J. C. Callaway, “<a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10681-004-4811-6" target="_blank">Hempseed as a nutritional resource: An overview</a>,” <em>Euphytica</em>, vol. 140, no. 1-2, pp. 65–72, 2004.</li> 
<li class="ref">X. S. Wang, C. H. Tang, X. Q. Yang, and W. R. Gao, “<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0308814607006358" target="_blank">Characterization, amino acid composition and in vitro digestibility of hemp (Cannabis sativa L.) proteins</a>,” <em>Food Chemistry</em>, vol. 107, no. 1, pp. 11–18, 2008.</li> 
<li class="ref">J. D. House, J. Neufeld, and G. Leson, “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20977230" target="_blank">Evaluating the quality of protein from hemp seed (Cannabis sativa L.) products through the use of the protein digestibility-corrected amino acid score method.</a>,” <em>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</em>, vol. 58, no. 22, pp. 11801–11807, 2010.</li> 
<li class="ref">C. J. Detzel, B. W. Petschow, N. Johnson, and E. M. Weaver, “<a href="https://www.ffhdj.com/index.php/ffhd/article/view/308" target="_blank">Comparison of the Amino Acid and Peptide Composition and Postprandial Response of Beef, Chicken, and Whey Protein Nutritional Preparations</a>,” <em>Functional Foods in Health and Disease</em>, vol. 6, no. 10, pp. 612–626, 2016.</li> 
</ol>]]></description>
        <pubDate>Mon Nov 05 2018 21:59:21 GMT+0800 (Australian Western Standard Time)</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>The Golden Zone</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>There is a damaging and pervasive myth in the health and fitness industry. </p>
<p>Actually there’s a bunch of them, but this is a big one: <strong>the myth that eating <em>healthy</em> food will help you lose weight</strong>.  </p>
<p>If you’ve ever been on a diet, you might have experienced being bombarded with people’s recommendations to eat a particular food because it is “<em>healthy</em>”.</p>
<p>It’s repeated by everyone from <a href="/blog/healthy-organic-post" target="_blank" title='A Healthy, Organic, Naturally Flavoured Post'>malicious marketers</a> to well-meaning grandparents. </p>
<p>This recommendation contains the implicit assumption that <em>healthy</em> and <em>low calorie</em> are inseparable concepts. </p>
<p>The malicious marketer is delighted that you don’t understand the difference between <em>healthy</em> and <em>low calorie</em>. It allows them to label their product as one and know that you’ll assume the other. </p>
<p>Your well-meaning granny has no idea that there is a difference between <em>healthy</em> and <em>low calorie</em>. She just wants you to be happy. </p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--head">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/granny-raisin-cookies.jpg" alt="Grandma holding a plate of raisin cookies.">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> “<em>I baked you some healthy raisin cookies for your new diet!</em>” </p>

<p>Although granny means the best, there is a huge difference between calling a food <em>healthy</em> and calling it <em>low calorie</em>. </p>
<p><strong><em>Healthy</em></strong> is used to describe foods that have a lot of micronutrients and/or other elements that improve your health in one way or another. Elements like <em>antioxidants</em> to help reduce free radicals (unstable molecules), <em>anthocyanins</em> for your brain, or <em>fibre</em> to help you poop. </p>
<p><strong><em>Low calorie</em></strong> is used to describe foods that are low in calories (<em><a href="https://media.giphy.com/media/xT0xeJpnrWC4XWblEk/giphy.gif" target="_blank" title='Mind = Blown.'>whoa</a></em>). Calories are a measure of the energy inside your food. When you consume more energy than you expend, the remaining energy is stored as fat (<em>or muscle if you’re doing it right</em>).  When you consume less energy than you expend, your body breaks down fat (<em>or muscle</em>) to make up the difference. So eating <em>low calorie</em> food is a great way to lose weight. </p>
<p>Notice how the definition of <em>healthy</em> didn’t include any mention of weight loss? And the definition of <em>low calorie</em> didn’t include any mention of health? That’s because <em>healthy</em> ≠ <em>low calorie</em>. </p>
<p><strong><em>Healthy food does not have to be low calorie, and low calorie food does not have to be healthy.</em></strong> </p>
<p>But that’s not to say it can’t be. When a food is both <em>healthy</em> and <em>low calorie</em>, that’s <strong>The Golden Zone</strong>.</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--head">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/the-golden-zone.png" alt="A two circle Venn diagram with healthy on one side, and low calorie on the other. The Golden Zone is the overlap between the two circles.">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Healthy + Low Calorie = The Golden Zone </p>

<p>The Golden Zone is the overlap between healthy and low calorie. These are the foods that tick all of your nutritional boxes. </p>
<p><strong><em>Golden Zone foods are healthy.</em></strong>  Depending on which food, this could mean protection against heart disease and cancer, reduced inflammation, improved memory, better insulin sensitivity, and many other characteristics that we associate with good health.  </p>
<p><strong><em>Golden Zone foods are low in calories.</em></strong> This makes them great for keeping you full, and helping you lose weight. </p>
<p>Examples of Golden Zone foods are: white fish, eggs, cottage cheese, and most vegetables (<em>full table <a href="/blog/the-golden-zone#table" target="_blank" title='Healthy, Low Calorie or Golden Zone.'>shown here</a></em>). They are nutrient dense from both a calorie and volume perspective, which means they will help keep you full in the moment <em>and</em> healthy long term.</p>
<p>A diversified diet rich in Golden Zone foods is ideal for weight management and long term health. That translates to a better looking, more athletic, and disease-free you. </p>
<p>So this begs the question… how many eggs do you have to eat before your 6 pack shows up?  Are you allowed to eat anything that’s not a Golden Zone food? And wasn’t eating an ‘<em>apple a day</em>’ already enough to avoid medical intervention entirely? </p>
<p>Well let’s back up a bit. First off, there are at least 2 good reasons to avoid eating Golden Zone foods. </p>
<h3>Reason #1: You’re Bulking</h3><p>Bulking is intentionally eating in a calorie surplus in an attempt to gain weight. We almost always want this weight in the form of muscle, not fat (<em>with sumo wrestlers being the obvious exception</em>). </p>
<p>Some people have difficulty eating enough food during a bulk to reach their calorie target. If you’re one of those people, then you have good reason to not eat Golden Zone foods. </p>
<p>Why? Well since Golden Zone foods are low calorie – and you’re struggling to get enough calories – you’re better off sticking to the pure <em>healthy</em> zone foods. This will allow you to more easily hit your calorie targets whilst still getting a large amount of nutrients. </p>
<p>To help hit your calorie targets, some common substitutions include: </p>
<ul>
<li>Replacing chicken breast with fattier cuts of beef. </li>
<li>Replacing almonds with macadamias. </li>
<li>Replacing spinach with sweet potatoes. </li>
<li>Replacing toothpaste with peanut butter. </li>
</ul>
<p>Etc. Now this obviously doesn’t make Golden Zone foods ‘<em>bad for you</em>’ in this situation. They’re just not the best choice, given your goals. </p>
<h3>Reason #2: You’re Human</h3><p>A bit tongue-in-cheek, but this will present itself in one way or another. If you’re in this for the long term, then you’re guaranteed to find yourself in many situations that make 100% clean eating near impossible. </p>
<p>Situations like: </p>
<ul>
<li>Having a big night out with the boys after getting a promotion</li>
<li>Your boss offering you their home-baked cookies the morning of your performance review </li>
<li>Dominoes cheaper Tuesdays </li>
</ul>
<p>Etc. In all seriousness, there are practical reasons to not eat Golden Zone foods. Sometimes they won’t be available. Sometimes you’ll splurge during a special event.</p>
<p>Alternatively... you could <strong><em>intentionally</em></strong> include unhealthy food as a part of your diet.</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new13">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/my-cookies.gif" alt="Arnold Schwarzenegger: 'Who told you you could eat my cookies?'">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> But you didn’t hear it from me.</p>

<h3>Eating the Cookie on Purpose</h3><p>Let me start with a quote from nutrition researcher <a href="https://alanaragon.com/about-alan/" target="_blank" title='Who is Alan Aragon?'>Alan Aragon</a> from his book <a href="https://amzn.to/2C6xxVJ" target="_blank" title='Amazon: The Lean Muscle Diet'>The Lean Muscle Diet</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Dietary perfection is a myth. It doesn’t exist. There is no Unicorn Diet for humans. Ten percent of the diet coming from anything you want might sound rebellious until you switch things around and see that 90 percent of the diet is a diligent effort to cover all the bases…”</p>
<p>– Alan Aragon </p>
</blockquote>
<p>Alan recommends taking a 90/10 approach to dieting:</p>
<ul>
<li>90% from whole and minimally processed foods (<em>with some exceptions, like <a href="https://lipidworld.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1476-511X-11-67" target="_blank" title='Health Benefits of Whey Protein'>whey protein</a></em>)</li>
<li>10% from whatever you want (<em>which Alan calls “pure junky goodness”</em>)</li>
</ul>
<p>Alan also shares a few anecdotes of people who have lived for a very long time while subsisting on common “<em>junk</em>” foods. Like the <a href="http://www.nbcnews.com/id/13119227/ns/health-diet_and_nutrition/t/man-lived-sausage-and-waffles-diet/" target="_blank" title='Man lived to 112 on sausage-and-waffles diet'>late George Johnson</a> who lived to 112 years old eating ‘<em>a diet largely of sausages and waffles</em>’. </p>
<p>Quite a few of the longest-living humans also seem to have had a weak spot for chocolate. </p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new14">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/eating-chocolate.gif" alt="Homer eating brownies.">
</picture><p class ="figurecap">“<em>Did he just say chocolate is good for me?</em>”</p>

<p>While I don’t find these anecdotes all that convincing on their own – they feel similar to the stories smokers tell you of their 99-year-old chain-smoking marathon-running grandpa – there is wisdom within Alan’s recommendation.</p>
<p>There are <em>diminishing returns</em> to the benefits of eating micronutrient-rich sources of food. Studies that show the largest benefits are almost always in the context of <strong><em>correcting a deficiency</em></strong>. This is fundamentally different to putting the finishing touches on an otherwise admirable diet. </p>
<p>If you are eating fish every day, then you won’t see much benefit taking fish oil. If you are in the sun for most of the day, then you won’t see much benefit taking vitamin D. And if you’re eating a lot of fruit, then you won’t see much benefit taking vitamin C.</p>
<p>Why? Because <strong><em>you don’t get bonus points for going over your micronutrient needs</em></strong>.</p>
<p>Now all this is based on the notion that you’re able to cover all your bases with <em>only</em> 90% of your diet. Which you most definitely can – <em>if</em> you’re eating whole and minimally processed foods. That translates to food in the <em>healthy</em> zone. </p>
<p>If you’re eating Golden Zone foods, you’ll be able to cover your bases with ~80% of your diet. Why? Well that’s 80% of your diet calorie-wise. So Golden Zone foods – which are by definition nutrient dense and low calorie – are a great way to get the nutrients you need without going over your calorie budget. </p>
<p>Vegetables get a special shout out here for being low calorie with a <em>diverse assortment</em> of vitamins and minerals – see <a href="http://www.whfoods.com/genpage.php?tname=foodspice&dbid=9" target="_blank" title='The Health Benefits of Broccoli'>broccoli</a> and <a href="http://www.whfoods.com/genpage.php?tname=foodspice&dbid=43" target="_blank" title='The Health Benefits of Spinach'>spinach</a> for great examples. </p>
<h3 id="numbers">Crunching the Numbers</h3>

<p>Let’s say you <a href="/calorie-calculator/" target="_blank" title='Calorie and Macronutrient Calculator'>calculate your calories</a> to be 2000 calories per day. 10-20% of that gives you 200-400 calories/day of “<em>pure junky goodness</em>” to work with. We’ll take the average of 300 calories/day for the below examples. </p>
<p>You can consume these ~300 calories as a “<em>daily treat</em>”, or you can bank the calories and use several days’ worth in one sitting. Some ideas: </p>
<ul>
<li>1 Original Glazed Krispy Kreme every day (<a class="no-ul" href="https://www.krispykreme.com.au/media/wysiwyg/pdf/Nutritional-Information.pdf" target="_blank" title='Calories in a Krispy Kreme'>~193 cal</a>) </li>
<li>1 KitKat Chocolate bar every day (<a class="no-ul" href="https://www.kitkat.co.uk/content/kitkatcollection/FourFinger" target="_blank" title='Calories in a KitKat'>~209 cal</a>; <em>the full 4 fingers – not the recommended 2 finger “serving size”</em>) </li>
<li>200g of Cookies &amp; Cream Connoisseur Ice Cream every 2 days (<a class="no-ul" href="http://www.connoisseuricecream.com.au/tubs/" target="_blank" title='Calories in Connoisseur Ice Cream'>~540 cal</a>; <em>I doubt anyone has ever followed the 64g “serving size”</em>) </li>
<li>5 slices of Dominoes BBQ Meatloves pizza every 3 days (<a class="no-ul" href="https://www.dominos.com.au/media/90963/traditional-range-2018.pdf" target="_blank" title='Calories in Dominos Pizza'>~810 cal</a>) </li>
<li>1 large Big Mac Meal every 5 days (<a class="no-ul" href="https://www.mcdonalds.co.za/menuItem/big-mac-meal" target="_blank" title='Calories in McDonalds Big Mac Meal'>~1476 cal</a>) </li>
</ul>
<p>Knowing how many calories are in your favourite junk foods helps you make more satisfying meal choices. </p>
<p>For instance, the above dot points tell me that I should never go to McDonalds. Why? Because not only do I prefer the <em>taste</em> of pizza over a Big Mac, but it’s also a <em>lot</em> less calories for what I would consider a satiating meal. So going to Dominoes instead of McDonalds makes sense from a taste <em>and</em> calorie point of view. </p>
<p>Now if you <em>love</em> McDonalds and crave a Big Mac above all else, then that’s fine too. If you’re happy with the trade-off, then enjoy a guilt-free Big Mac. </p>
<p>As long as you stay within your <em>calorie budget</em> – spend your junk calories on whatever food your taste buds’ desire. </p>
<h3>Wrapping it Up</h3><p>You could be forgiven for forgetting this post was about eating healthy, low calorie foods – not optimising how much pizza you can cram into your diet. </p>
<p>Some take-away points: </p>
<ul>
<li>Healthy and low calorie mean very different things </li>
<li>You can’t go wrong eating Golden Zone food – food that is both healthy and low calorie</li>
<li>It’s okay to eat <em>pure junky goodness</em> sometimes – approximately 10-20% of your diet is fine</li>
</ul>
<p>There is no one way to diet – just as there is no one way to parent a child or roast a turkey. But there are terrible ways to do all three. </p>
<p><strong>So don’t get burned by another fad diet.</strong></p>
<p>Think about the food in the Golden Zone that <strong>you</strong> enjoy the most. Basing your diet around this food is an effective and practical way to achieve <strong><em>lasting</em></strong> aesthetics and health. </p>
<p>And since we’re creating <strong>a diet that will last</strong>, we will include some room for indulgence.   </p>
<h3 id="table">Healthy, Low Calorie, or Golden Zone</h3>

<p>The table below gives typical examples of Healthy, Low Calorie, and Golden Zone foods.</p>
<p>The table is <strong><em>not</em></strong> comprehensive – in part because there are too many foods in existence to classify. But it should be more than enough to get started. </p>
<p>There are always going to be edge cases and points of disagreement, and I’ve added a few footnotes to address some of these. You can <a href="mailto:info@musclehacking.com" target="_blank" title='Muscle Hacking Email'>email me</a> if you would like to suggest a change. </p>
<div class="table-responsive">
  <table id="gz-table"class="table">
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th id="th-5" scope="col" style="width: 33%; min-width: 150px;">Healthy</th>
        <th id="th-6" scope="col" style="width: 33%; min-width: 150px;">Golden Zone</th>
        <th id="th-7" scope="col" style="width: 33%; min-width: 150px;">Low Calorie</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td id="tr-5">
        <ul id="t-li1">
            <li>Salmon (with skin)</li>
            <li>Avocado</li>
            <li>Beef (fattier cuts)</li>
            <li>Lamb</li>
            <li>Pork</li>
            <li>Macadamias</li>
            <li>Pecans</li>
            <li>Pine nuts</li>
            <li>Brazil nuts</li>
            <li>Walnuts</li>
            <li>Hazelnuts</li>
            <li>Sunflower seeds &dagger;</li>
            <li>Peanut butter</li>
            <li>Beans &dagger;</li>
            <li>Lugumes &dagger;</li>
            <li>Whole milk</li>
            <li>Full-fat cheese</li>
            <li>Brown rice &dagger;</li>
            <li>Quinoa &dagger;</li>
       </ul>
        </td>
        <td id="tr-6">
        <ul id="t-li2">
            <li>White fish</li>
            <li>Chicken (skinless)</li>
            <li>Turkey (skinless)</li>
            <li>Beef (lean)</li>
            <li>Eggs</li>
            <li>Cottage cheese</li>
            <li>Vegetables&circ; (<em>fresh or frozen</em>)</li>
            <li>Fruit &#9824; (<em>fresh or frozen</em>)</li>
            <li>Yogurt (<em><b>not</b></em> the brands loaded with sugar)</li>
            <li>Almonds &dagger;</li>
            <li>Pistachios &dagger;</li>
            <li>Cashew nuts &dagger;</li>
            <li>Chestnuts</li>
            <li>Pumpkin seeds &dagger;</li>
            <li>Oats</li>
            <li>Low-fat milk</li>
            <li>Whey protein</li>
            <li>Casein protein</li>
            <li>Scallops</li>
            <li>Sardines</li>
            <li>Muscles</li>
            <li>Shrimp</li>
        <ul>
        </td>
        <td id="tr-7">
        <ul id="t-li3">
        <li>Zero-calorie soft drink (<em>Diet Coke, Pepsi Max, etc.</em>)</li>
        <li>Sugar-free candy</li>
        <li><a href="https://www.woolworths.com.au/shop/productdetails/252668/queen-sugar-free-maple-syrup" target="_blank" title='Queens Sugar-Free Maple Syrup'>Sugar-free maple syrup</a></li>
        <li><a href="http://www.aeroplanejelly.com.au/our-products/jelly-lite/lite-cranberry-raspberry" target="_blank" title='Aeroplane Jelly Lite '>Low calorie jelly</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://www.fiberone.com/products/sweet-treats/cinnamon-coffee-cake" target="_blank" title='Cinnamon Coffee Cake'>Low calorie cakes</a></li>
        </ul>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</div>

<p>&circ; Potatoes, sweet potatoes, corn, and green peas are on the line between Healthy and Golden Zone.</p>
<p>&#9824; Figs and mangoes are on the line between Healthy and Golden Zone.</p>
<p>&dagger; These foods are on the line between Healthy and Golden Zone. The final decision as Healthy/Golden Zone was made by considering how filling a standard serving size is relative to comparable Healthy/Golden Zone foods. For example, comparing the calories and satiation for a serving of brown rice vs. a serving of oats.</p>
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Mon Nov 05 2018 21:59:21 GMT+0800 (Australian Western Standard Time)</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>The Australian Health Star Disaster</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>The Australian Government has come up with a fantastic new way to keep their taxpayers trim.</p>
<p>It’s ingenious. </p>
<p>They label each food with a <strong><em>health star rating</em></strong> out of 5. </p>
<p>The full 5 stars is reserved for only the most audacious of health foods. Think 17-Grain-Gluten-Free quinoa.</p>
<p>Eating healthy has never been so easy. 6 pack abs is now within reach to anyone that can count to 5. </p>
<p>Maccas might as well pack up shop now. Colonel Sanders’ reign is over. Long live the standing desk. The <a href="https://www.aihw.gov.au/reports-statistics/behaviours-risk-factors/overweight-obesity/overview" target="_blank" title='Obesity in Australia'>Australian obesity epidemic</a>  is over – <em>Right?</em></p>
<p>There are many complexities and nuances to nutrition. So did the government really succeed in simplifying this complexity to a star rating out of 5?</p>
<p>.... <strong>nope</strong>.</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--16x9">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/pickle-heath-star.jpg" alt="Pickle Rick Boom Big Reveal">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> <em><b>Boom, big reveal</b></em> (3.5 stars) </p>

<p>What does a food being “<em>healthy</em>” mean to you? </p>
<p>Although you can point to some foods you would consider healthy, you might find defining it to be a challenge. You would be in close company.</p>
<p>If you were to ask 10 different people, you would get 10 different definitions. These explanations are often quite hand-wavey, prompting further questions (what exactly does “<em>good for you</em>” mean Stacey?).</p>
<p>And that’s exactly what the Australian Health Star Rating does. Prompt further questions. Like “<em>who in their right mind would advocate such terrible nutritional advice</em>”.</p>
<p>But we’re getting ahead of ourselves. Just what is a “Health Star Rating”? According to the <a href="http://healthstarrating.gov.au/internet/healthstarrating/publishing.nsf/Content/About-health-stars" target="_blank" title='What is a Health Star Rating?'>Health Star Rating website</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>“The Health Star Rating is a front-of-pack labelling system that rates the overall nutritional profile of packaged food and assigns it a rating from ½ a star to 5 stars. It provides a quick, easy, standard way to compare similar packaged foods. The more stars, the healthier the choice.”</em>  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>You read right – <strong>The more stars, the healthier the choice</strong>. It turns out that the nuances of nutrition were all in our head! The government managed to compact these complexities into 5 simple stars. </p>
<p>Before I wrap up this post, we had better have a look at some of these ratings:</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--16x9">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/salmon-heath-star.jpg" alt="Salmon 3.5 Health Star Rating">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Atlantic Salmon – 3.5 Health Stars </p>
<br>

<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--16x10">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/nutrigrain-heath-star.jpg" alt="Nutrigrain 4 Health Star Rating">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Nutrigrain – 4 Health Stars </p>
<br>

<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--16x9">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/beer-batter-chips-heath-star.jpg" alt="Beer Batter Chips 4 Health Star Rating">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Beer Batter Fries – 4 Health Stars </p>
<br>

<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new12">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/milo-heath-star.jpg" alt="Milo 4.5 Health Star Rating">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Milo – 4.5 Health Stars </p>

<p>Huh? That doesn’t seem right. Didn’t more stars mean more healthy? </p>
<p>Beer batter fries aren’t usually what comes to mind when we think of health foods. And isn’t Milo just sugar? </p>
<p>Well, remember this part of the Health Star definition: </p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>“...It provides a quick, easy, standard way to <strong>compare similar packaged foods</strong>.”</em>  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>Similar. Packaged. Foods. Oh. So we’re not comparing chicken breast to quinoa. <strong><em>We’re comparing beer battered fries to chilli cheese fries</em></strong>. That’s not useful, that’s just misleading.</p>
<p>And what is a “<em>similar packaged food</em>” exactly? Are we comparing breakfast cereals with other breakfast choices – like eggs or oats – or only against other breakfast cereals. Is the relative “<em>healthiness</em>” of <a href="https://www.kelloggs.com.au/en_AU/brands/coco-pops.html" target="_blank" title='Kellogg‘s Coco Pops'>Coco Pops</a> vs  <a href="https://www.kelloggs.com.au/en_AU/brands/froot-loops.html" target="_blank" title='Kellogg‘s Fruit Loops'>Fruit Loops</a> useful to anyone with more than 3 brain cells? </p>
<p>So what is a “<em>similar packaged food</em>” that we’re comparing Milo to exactly... Nesquik?</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--16x9">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/nesquik-heath-star.jpg" alt="Nesquik Health Star Rating">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Nesquik – ?? Health Stars </p>

<p>Looks like Nesquik doesn’t have a Health Star Rating. And herein lies another problem with Health Stars – <a href="http://healthstarrating.gov.au/internet/healthstarrating/publishing.nsf/Content/About-health-stars" target="_blank" title='Who developed the Health Star Rating system?'><strong><em>it’s a voluntary rating system</em></strong></a>. That’s right. Don’t like your dodgy rating? No worries – just don’t show it! </p>
<p>This still doesn’t explain how chocolate-coated sugar (Milo) got a 4.5 star health rating. Even compared to deep-fried ice cream Milo doesn’t deserve 4.5 stars. </p>
<p>Well lucky for Milo, there is an “<em>as prepared</em>” rule. This allows companies to rate products based on their suggested recipe for preparation rather than their standalone nutritional value. And how do we prepare Milo? We <del>inject it directly into our blood stream</del> have it with a 200ml glass of skim milk. </p>
<p>Milo + Skim Milk = 4.5 stars. If Milo’s healthiness was based on its own merits, <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/radio/programs/am/food-industry-stalling-on-health-star-rule-review/9032848" target="_blank" title='Food industry stalling on health star rule review'>it would get 1.5 stars.</a> </p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--70">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/milo-skim-milk-health-star.jpg" alt="Nesquik Health Star Rating">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> The Magic of “<em>As Prepared</em>” </p>

<p>Since skim milk is <a href="http://www.abs.gov.au/ausstats/abs@.nsf/Lookup/by%20Subject/4364.0.55.007~2011-12~Main%20Features~Milk%20products%20and%20dishes~721" target="_blank" title='Australian Health Survey - Milk Products and Dishes'>only 11% of consumed dairy milk</a>, that’s <em>probably</em> not how the Milo was prepared. Not to forget the people who forgo the milk altogether. Anything from “<a href="http://thesmartlocal.com/read/milo-recipes" target="_blank" title='How People Really Eat Milo'><em>Easy Fried Milo French Toast</em></a>” to taking it straight from the spoon (<em>like a normal person</em>).</p>
<p>By that logic sugar deserves at least a 4 Health Star Rating. After all, it is <em>intended</em> to be “<em>as prepared</em>” in a coffee with skim milk. </p>
<p>Coffee + skim milk + sugar = 4 stars. Now I can stick a big “<em>4 Health Star Rating</em>” label on my sugar, and still sleep well at night knowing that my product has more nutritional integrity than Milo.</p>
<p>Arguably the best part about the new health star rating is its direct contradiction to other government recommendations. The <a href="https://www.eatforhealth.gov.au/guidelines" target="_blank" title='Australian Dietary Guidelines'>Australian Dietary Guidelines</a> takes a whole-foods approach to dieting, encouraging Australians to eat a wide variety of nutritious foods. It even <a href="https://www.eatforhealth.gov.au/guidelines/about-australian-dietary-guidelines" target="_blank" title='How do I make healthy food choices?'>calls out the bad tendency fad-diet’s have</a> of unnecessarily strict diet restrictions (<em>cough</em> Paleo Diet <em>cough</em>): </p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The advice focuses on dietary patterns that promote health and wellbeing rather than recommending that you eat – or completely avoid – specific foods.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That actually sounds reasonable. The infographic is pretty good too: </p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--3">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/australian-guide-to-healthy-eating.jpg" alt="The Australian Guide to Healthy Eating">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> The Australian Guide to Healthy Eating </p>

<p>Definitely not perfect (<em>the biggest section should <strong>not</strong> be grain foods</em>), but reasonable. </p>
<p>In contrast, the Health Star Rating system bases its healthiness on the nutritional composition of the food. Give <a href="http://healthstarrating.gov.au/internet/healthstarrating/publishing.nsf/Content/online-calculator#/step/1" target="_blank" title='Health Star Rating Online Calculator'>the online calculator</a> a product’s energy, saturated fat, total sugars, sodium, protein, fibre, and % fruit and vegetable content, and it will spit out a star rating. Because <em>that’s all that matters</em> when it comes to eating healthy! </p>
<p>These two rating systems take a very different approach to evaluating the “<em>healthiness</em>” of a food. Notice in the above infographic our beloved 4 star beer batter fries receive the worst rating of “<em>Only sometimes and in small amounts</em>”. Whoops. </p>
<p>Nutrition can be confusing enough on its own without the government contradicting itself. The point of the rating system was to provide a simple way for people to understand how “<em>healthy</em>” a product is. </p>
<p>It was targeted at those who – whether due to time restrictions, different priorities, or confusion caused by the hundreds of conflicting opinions – are in the dark when it comes to nutrition.</p>
<p>The target market is certainly not the type to read the fine print on the back of a box. Or go onto the Health Star Rating website to understand the details of how the stars are allocated. </p>
<p>They’re the type to quickly count the number of stars on the label and use that as an indication for how healthy the product is. This seems to have been the <em>intent</em> of the Heath Star Rating system, it just got lost in the nonsense of “<em>as prepared</em>” and “<em>similar packaged food</em>”. Now the system is fanning the already hot flames of confusion that surround nutrition.</p>
<p>In short: the Australian Health Star Rating system is a castle in the air, connected to the ground by thin strings of nutritional science. </p>
<p>Don’t rely on it for anything other than a good laugh.</p>
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Mon Nov 05 2018 21:59:21 GMT+0800 (Australian Western Standard Time)</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>A Healthy, Organic, Naturally Flavoured Post</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Healthy. Organic. Gluten free. Fat free. No Added Sugar. Do these labels sound familiar? </p>
<p>They’re a great way for a company to sincerely inform you of the positive aspects of their product. </p>
<p>But more often than not, they’re used to mislead you into believing that what you’re buying is somehow “<em>good for you</em>”. </p>
<p>This leads to problems if you’re not aware of <em>exactly</em> what a claim means.</p>
<p>Let’s look at a typical example:</p>
<ul>
<li>Stacey has just started a new diet, and is browsing her local supermarket</li>
<li>Stacey buys a pack of nut bars that claim to be a <em>“healthy snack”</em></li>
<li>Every time Stacey gets hungry between meals, she nibbles on a nut bar</li>
<li>2 weeks and a couple boxes later, Stacey is 2 pounds heavier</li>
</ul>
<p>This can be a very frustrating experience for Stacey, who was under the impression that replacing her favourite chocolate with this <em>“healthy snack”</em> would help her lose weight. </p>
<p>Stacey’s weight loss woes can be attributed to clever marketing blended with a lack consumer understanding. Like many people, Stacey has associated the word <em>“healthy”</em> to <em>“low calorie”</em>.  <strong><em>But “healthy” and “low calorie” do not mean the same thing.</em></strong>  </p>
<p>Food is usually deemed <em>healthy</em> (or <em>“good for you”</em>) if it has a lot of <a href="https://www.nal.usda.gov/fnic/vitamins-and-minerals" target="_blank" title="Micronutrient defined">micronutrients</a> (i.e. vitamins &amp; minerals), regardless of its <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/public-health-nutrition/article/macronutrients-as-sources-of-food-energy/DDF89DE14E92D39D56A45FBAA3F00A55 " target="_blank" title="Macronutrient defined">macronutrient</a> content. Macronutrients are fat, protein and carbohydrates. They define the calorie content of your food,  and hence the success of your weight loss efforts. </p>
<p>If Stacey were brave enough to flip the box and read the nutrition label, she would find that these <em>healthy</em> nut bars have a <em>lot</em> of fat in them. </p>
<p>Although many would argue these to be <em>“healthy fats”</em>, this does not relieve them of their high calorie content – easily leading to unwanted weight gain if you’re not careful with your portion sizes.</p>
<p>Note that the supplier hasn’t actually lied about their product. Nuts are <em>healthy</em>. It’s just that food can be <em>healthy</em> without being low in calories – nuts being a prime example. </p>
<p>The <a href="/blog/the-golden-zone" target="_blank" title="Difference between Healthy and Low Calorie">confusion between <em>healthy</em> and <em>low calorie</em></a> can lead people to believe that a product is something it’s not.</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/walnuts-vs-chocolate.jpg" alt="Calories in Chocolate vs. Walnuts">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Walnuts actually contain more calories per gram than chocolate, with around ~65 calories/10g, while chocolate is ~50-60 calories/10g <a title="Calories in Walnuts" target="_blank" href="https://ndb.nal.usda.gov/ndb/foods/show/12155?fgcd=&manu=&format=&count=&max=25&offset=&sort=default&order=asc&qlookup=walnut&ds=SR&qt=&qp=&qa=&qn=&q=&ing=">[1]</a>
<a title="Calories in Chocolate" target="_blank" href="https://ndb.nal.usda.gov/ndb/foods/show/19081?man=&lfacet=&count=&max=25&qlookup=chocolate&offset=&sort=default&format=Abridged&reportfmt=other&rptfrm=&ndbno=&nutrient1=&nutrient2=&nutrient3=&subset=&totCount=&measureby=&Qv=1&Q333352=1&Q333353=1&Qv=10&Q333352=1&Q333353=1">[2]</a></p> 

<p>Nut bars aren’t evil. </p>
<p>They’re just one of the many products who are a regular target of disingenuous marketing.</p>
<p>Candy is another common target, which frequently boasts about having <em>“No Artificial Colours or Flavours”</em> or being <em>“99% Fat Free”</em>. </p>
<p>The number of people who read these labels and think <em>“These are good for me”</em> is concerning. Once familiar with this type of advertising, you’ll instead instantly conclude: <em>“Made with 100% Sugar”</em>.</p>
<p>Now I’m not saying that sugar is the devil and you should avoid it at all costs – because it definitely isn’t and you definitely shouldn’t. </p>
<p><strong><em>But when you indulge on a sweet treat it’s important to be aware that it is just that – a sweet treat</em></strong>.</p>
<p>Otherwise there’ll be no guilt holding you back from heading down to your local McDonalds and ordering a big mac and fries for round 2. I mean, why not – you’ve eaten so well today! </p>
<p>An eating habit like this can easily lead to unwanted weight gain.</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new2">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/majin-buu-eating.gif" alt="Eating cake">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Don’t worry – it’s Gluten Free </p>

<p>This isn’t purely a marketing problem. </p>
<p>If a candy company wants to accurately label its product as having <em>“No Artificial Colours or Flavours”</em>, they should be able to. That way those looking to buy candy without artificial colours or flavours will be able to easily identify what products they can choose from.</p>
<p>To fix this issue long term, we need to bridge the gap in consumer knowledge. <em>“No Artificial Colours or Flavours”</em> on a pack of candy should not distract you from the candy’s 100% sugar content.</p>
<p>Although it would be convenient, it’s unrealistic to expect a company to actively market such information. Until crooked teeth become fashionable, we probably won’t see:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“No artificial colours or flavours. Boatloads of sugar.”</p>
<p>— Nestl&eacute;  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>The underlying issue is the <a title="Information asymmetry defined." target="_blank" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information_asymmetry "><strong><em>information asymmetry</em></strong></a> between suppliers and consumers. Suppliers know exactly what’s in their products. Consumers don’t. </p>
<p>So a consumer must read and interpret a product’s labelling. But <strong><em>the goal of most labelling is to sell, not to inform</em></strong>. So a consumer must be able to correctly interpret what a label (or buzzword) means.</p>
<p>Although the average consumer is better at reading a label than they used to be, that doesn’t say much. </p>
<p>I’ve known people who thought a product was <em>“healthy”</em> purely because it was labelled <em>“Low in salt!”</em> – which is what I imagine a marketer’s wet dream to be like.</p>
<p>Not to forget: </p>
<ul>
<li>High sugar cereals that justify being good for kids because of the vitamins and minerals they smuggle into the ingredients list.</li>
<li><em>“No Added Cane Sugar!”</em> drinks that swap the cane sugar for fruit sugar (fructose). </li>
<li>The <em>“Heart Foundation Tick of Approval”</em> being slapped onto anything low in fat. </li>
</ul>
<p>With all these options available to mislead the uninformed consumer, it’s no wonder that people find proper nutrition to be so disheartenedly confusing.</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--head">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/shopping.jpg" alt="Woman holding shopping bags filled with healthy foods">
</picture><p class ="figurecap fig-centre"> “<em>What the heck is a ‘Wholegrain Tick’?</em>” </p>

<p>So let’s shed some light on some of the most common and pernicious marketing techniques.
The table below outlines:</p>
<ol>
<li>Common food labels</li>
<li>What they’re generally interpreted to mean</li>
<li>What they really mean</li>
<li>What to keep in mind when you read them (red flags)</li>
</ol>
<p>I’ve also mentioned the types of food that typically feature these labels. Stacey’s love handles never stood a chance.</p>
<div class="table-responsive">
  <table id="ho-table" class="table">
    <thead class="thead-dark">
      <tr>
        <th id="th-1" scope="col" style="width: 20%; min-width: 125px;">Label</th>
        <th id="th-2" scope="col" style="width: 25%; min-width: 150px;">What Stacey Thinks It Means</th>
        <th id="th-3" scope="col" style="width: 25%; min-width: 180px; ">What It Really Means</th>
        <th id="th-4" scope="col" style="width: 30%; min-width: 200px;">What To Look Out For</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/gluten-free.jpg" alt="Gluten Free">
        </picture></th>
        <td>Somehow it has become common knowledge that anything gluten free is healthy.</td>
        <td>It lacks gluten, a protein found in wheat. ~1% of the population are unable to digest gluten.</td>
        <td>Everything. This is a red flag. Despite what some may tell you, a product being gluten free does not provide any information about its nutritional value.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/fat-free.jpg" alt="99% Fat Free">
        </picture></th>
        <td>Anything free of fat is good for me and/or will help me lose fat.</td>
        <td>The product has less than 1% of its calories derived from fat.</td>
        <td>High sugar content. It’s a very common label among candy companies. That is ridiculous since nearly all candy is inherently 99% Fat Free.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/low-salt.jpg" alt="Low in Salt">
        </picture></th>
        <td>Salt is the demon child of its sugar daddy. Thus, anything low in salt is good – <em>right?</em></td>
        <td>There isn’t much salt. That’s it. That’s all it means.</td>
        <td>Everything. A product bragging about this is a red flag.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/natural-ingredients.jpg" alt="All Natural Ingredients">
        </picture></th>
        <td>Anything natural is good for me.</td>
        <td>Natural is defined as “<em>something that exists in nature</em>”. For reference, Arsenic is also 100% natural (please don’t eat arsenic).</td>
        <td>Its fat and sugar content, especially the latter. Products that use a lot of sugar love this label.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/no-added-sugar.jpg" alt="No Added Sugar">
        </picture></th>
        <td><strong>(1)</strong> No added sugar is the same as having no sugar at all
  <strong>(2)</strong> It’s good for me, because sugar is always bad and I should avoid it.</td>
        <td>They haven’t added any sugar to their product. Note that a product can have a very high sugar content and still have no added sugar.</td>
        <td>Its fat, sugar, and calorie content. A stick of butter has no added sugar, but you wouldn’t assume it’s healthy just because I slapped that label on it would you?</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/vegan-friendly.jpg" alt="Vegan Friendly">
        </picture></th>
        <td>Vegans are typically skinny and healthy. So if vegans eat it, it must be good.</td>
        <td>No animal or animal products were used or harmed in the creation of the product.</td>
        <td>The calorie content. These products usually sit at the extremes, being either very low calorie (coconut water ice-cream) or very high calorie (nut-related products).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/organic-ingredients.jpg" alt="Organic Ingredients">
        </picture></th>
        <td>In the words of a friend: “<em>It means it’s clean</em>”.</td>
        <td>“<em>Organic agriculture produces products using methods that preserve the environment and avoid most synthetic materials, such as pesticides and antibiotics</em>”.</td>
        <td>Being good for the environment is great, but it is not a good indicator of its nutritional value.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/paleo-friendly.jpg" alt="Paleo Friendly">
        </picture></th>
        <td>My ancestors were nutrition experts. Thus anything Paleo MUST be healthy.</td>
        <td>Unnecessary restrictions on what you can and can’t eat (<a class="anchor"  href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M5kx9FrIhJU" target="_blank" title="Paleo Cream Puffs" ><em>why can’t I have my peanuts and coffee again?</em></a>).</td>
        <td>Everything. Although more specifically many paleo foods can be deceptively high in calories.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/heart-foundation-tick.jpg" alt="Heart Foundation Tick">
        </picture></th>
        <td>The Heart Foundation said it’s good for my heart. Hence it must be good for me.</td>
        <td>“<em>…varieties that are lower in saturated fat, trans fat, salt, and kilojoules, and contain ingredients and nutrients that are better for you, like fibre, calcium, whole grains and vegetables</em>” – The Heart Foundation</td>
        <td>The Heart Foundation is glued to the idea that fat is bad for the heart and sugar is a non-issue. As such, many foods with extremely high sugar levels have this tick.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/whole-grain-tick.jpg" alt="Whole Grain Tick">
        </picture></th>
        <td>I’m not sure what a whole grain is, but it sounds kind of nutritious.</td>
        <td>The grain has the bran, the endosperm, and the germ in tact. </td>
        <td>Having all three parts of the grain does not make a product healthy and/or low calorie. If this is the best a product has to brag about, it’s junk.</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</div>
<br>

<p>Hopefully this will help you on your next trip to the supermarket – or at the very least give you a good laugh. </p>
<p>I was dumbfounded when I first started flipping around boxes and reading the ingredients and nutrition panel of so-called “<em>healthy foods</em>”.</p>
<p>If a lot of what you’ve just read is new to you – you have been warned.</p>
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Mon Nov 05 2018 21:59:21 GMT+0800 (Australian Western Standard Time)</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>What is Intermittent Fasting?</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p><strong>“Don’t forget to eat your breakfast Jimmy – it’s the most important meal of the day!”</strong>
<br>
— Well meaning Mother</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Well meaning, but wrong. But who could blame her?</p>
<p>Anyone growing up from the 1960s to the 1980s who watched Saturday morning cartoons saw countless advertisements that emphasised the importance of breakfast.</p>
<p>Animated characters and jingles of all sorts taught kids not to head off to school before eating something. Otherwise they wouldn’t have any <em>energy</em>. They wouldn’t be able to <em>focus</em>. What they needed, was a <strong><em>“balanced breakfast”</em></strong>.</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new7">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/cheerios-bulk.jpg" alt="Cheerios Commercial">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> General Mill’s Cheerios: “<em>Energy O’s that help you grow</em>” </p>

<p>According to the TV a <em>“balanced breakfast”</em> may include: Cheerios, Cocoa Puffs, Lucky Charms, Trix, and/or Frosted Flakes. </p>
<p>These cereals battled it out to get into the cupboards of as many families as possible. Little Jimmy’s eating habits depended on which cereal had the coolest cartoon character, or the catchiest jingle.</p>
<p>But no matter which cereal won the battle, <strong>breakfast won the war</strong>. </p>
<p>It was a brutally effective strategy. How often have you heard that <strong><em>“Breakfast is the most important meal of the day”</em></strong>? It’s parroted to us so often that it is almost blasphemous to say otherwise.</p>
<p>Well it turns out that cereal companies may have had other motives when they crowned breakfast as the king of all meals.</p>
<p>Intermittent fasting points out that the noble Emperor Froot Loops III isn’t wearing any clothes.</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new6">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/apple-jacks.jpg" alt="Apple Jacks Commercial">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Kellog’s Apple Jacks: “<em>A bowl a day gives you energy to play</em>” </p>

<p>When you intermittently fast, you restrict your eating to a pre-defined period of the day. </p>
<p>This generally involves <strong>skipping your morning breakfast</strong>.</p>
<h3>Why Should I Intermittent Fast?</h3><p>Well first off: <strong>why do you eat when you eat right now?</strong> Have you ever actually thought about it? </p>
<p>You probably adopted the eating habits of your parents, who adopted the eating habits of their parents. But don’t blame Nanna – she was just following everyone else.</p>
<p>People tend to reinforce each other’s beliefs in self-perpetuating loops. Each round of mutual confirmation tightens our beliefs further. Until we have little choice but to believe what everyone else believes: <em>“Breakfast is the most important meal of the day”</em>. </p>
<p>So have we always eaten in the mornings? Did we evolve with an around-the-clock buffet, eating 5+ times per day? </p>
<p>No – <strong><em>we evolved with elongated periods of fasting and feeding</em></strong>. </p>
<p>Food was eaten when it was available. If you didn’t kill anything until 2pm, then you fasted until 2pm.</p>
<p>This begs the question – <strong>how did we manage to kill anything without any <em>energy</em> or <em>focus?</em></strong> </p>
<p>From a survival perspective, a lack of food warrants an increased level of concentration. We need to stay focused if we want to catch our next meal.</p>
<p>And this <strong><em>focus</em></strong> is exactly what you experience while fasting.</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new10">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/caveman-breakfast.jpg" alt="Caveman breakfast">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> <em>God Dammit Mum, I said I wanted Cheerios</em> </p>

<blockquote>
<p>“But every time I skip breakfast I’m starving – I can’t concentrate!”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I was the exact same. Worse than that – I would eat a big breakfast and be famished by 11am. <strong>Before I skipped breakfast, I tried everything to make it more satiating.</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>I was told oats were filling, so I ate oats in the mornings. <strong>Hungry at 11am.</strong></li>
<li>I was told fruit was filling, so I added fruit to my oats. <strong>Hungry at 11am.</strong></li>
<li>I was told protein was filling, so I added an egg to my oats (this tastes way better than it sounds). <strong>Hungry at 11am.</strong></li>
<li>I was told almonds were filling... you see the trend?</li>
</ul>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new5">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/oats-breakfast.jpg" alt="Oats for breakfast">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Delicious breakfast. Still hungry at 11am. </p>    

<p>I stumbled upon intermittent fasting in search of a better morning. </p>
<p>I was sick of the time lost making and eating breakfast. I was sick of the ups and downs in concentration. And most of all, <strong><em>I was sick of the hunger pangs.</em></strong></p>
<p>So when I heard that I could lose weight, save time, and increase my concentration via skipping breakfast, I was as skeptical as you. But I was willing to give it a shot, <strong>since my current eating habits <em>clearly</em> weren’t working.</strong></p>
<blockquote>
<p>“...when I heard that I could lose weight, save time, and increase my concentration via skipping breakfast, I was as skeptical as you.”    </p>
</blockquote>
<p>And oh boy was I hungry... for the first week. That’s roughly how long it will take for your hunger hormones to adjust to your new eating routine. After that, pure bliss. Now <strong>I enjoy more <em>time</em>, more <em>focus</em>, but <em>no more hunger.</em></strong></p>
<p>I’ve been intermittent fasting for over 4 years now, and I can’t see myself turning back. It’s amazing what a huge difference such a simple change can make.</p>
<h3>How Do I Intermittent Fast?</h3><p>Intermittent fasting divides your day into two periods. A fasting period, and a feeding period. The feeding period is also called an “<em>eating window”</em>.</p>
<p>No one is eating 24 hrs/day, so we are all fasting and feeding already.</p>
<p>But since we aren’t feeding with a plan in mind, we end up with too large an eating window. Plan “<em>Eat Whenever My Tummy Grumbles</em>” doesn’t count as a plan.</p>
<p>Although we <em>generally</em> stop eating at around 9pm, if your stomach growls at 11pm you might pop back into the kitchen for a snack.</p>
<p>We <em>usually</em> eat breakfast at 8am, but you’re <em>starving</em> this morning. So you have it a little earlier at 7am.</p>
<p>So we fast from our last scoop of ice cream at night to our first spoonful of cereal in the morning. This results in most people fasting for less than 12 hours, <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4250148/" target="_blank" title="Meal frequency and timing in health and disease">which is not ideal.</a> </p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new9">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/snacking-at-night.jpg" alt="Man eating sandwich in bed">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Just a nibble? </p>

<p>There are various fasting and feeding routines. A common and effective routine is an eating window from 12pm to 8pm each day (<em>made popular as the <a href="http://leangains.com/" target="_blank" title="leangains.com">leangains</a> routine</em>).</p>
<p>Under this routine you don’t start consuming any solid or liquid calories until 12pm, and you stop no later than 8pm.</p>
<p>This has myriad benefits compared to some alternate routines.</p>
<h3>What are the Benefits of Intermittent Fasting?</h3><p>First off, the consistent eating window <strong>regulates your hunger hormones</strong>. The reason your stomach rumbles at 8am is because your body is used to eating at 8am. It’s expecting food.</p>
<p>At your regular breakfast time, your body releases Ghrelin (<em>a hunger hormone</em>) and widens your stomach in preparation for food. <strong><em>This makes you hungry</em></strong>.</p>
<p>Now if you start eating at 12pm, your body adapts to your new eating habits. Your hunger will now develop at 12pm, not 8am. And just like that: <strong>no more morning hunger.</strong></p>
<p>By the same token, you’ll no longer be tempted to snack at night. If you consistently cut off your eating by 8pm, your body will no longer expect food past 8pm.</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--2">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/eating-in-bed.jpg" alt="Man eating midnight snacks in bed">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> No more midnight snacks </p>

<p>It gets better. <strong><em>When you have less time to eat, you eat less.</em></strong> </p>
<p>You might suspect that you’ll binge after not eating for so long. But most people find that they naturally eat less. This is especially true if you’re eating satiating foods.  <strong>There just isn’t enough time for your fullness to subside</strong>. </p>
<p>Granted you can still go into a calorie surplus if you go overboard.  If you only eat high calorie junk then you will still gain weight. But even then, it’s harder to do. </p>
<p>The fixed eating window is a one-two punch on weight loss. The left punch stops you snacking throughout the day. The right punch doesn’t give you time to regain your hunger. Before you know it, your hunger is knocked out cold. Weight loss becomes a breeze.</p>
<picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new11">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/strawberry-smiggles.jpg" alt="Strawberry smiggles">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> No longer tempted by strawberry smiggles </p>

<p>So intermittent fasting helps you:</p>
<ul>
<li>Get rid of your morning hunger</li>
<li>Improve your concentration</li>
<li>Save time</li>
<li>Eat less</li>
</ul>
<p>There is also emerging evidence that <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26094889 " target="_blank" title="A Periodic Diet that Mimics Fasting Promotes Multi-System Regeneration, Enhanced Cognitive Performance, and Healthspan">fasting can help you live longer</a>. Intermittent fasting and longevity will be explored more in another post. </p>
<p>If you’re currently fit, healthy, have plenty of spare time, and have no trouble staying focused, then keep on doing what you’re doing. But if you want to improve in any of these areas, then consider intermittent fasting. </p>
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Mon Nov 05 2018 21:59:21 GMT+0800 (Australian Western Standard Time)</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>How To Use The Calorie Calculator</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<div id="toc_container">
<p id="toc-h">Table of Contents</p>
<ul id='toc-ul'>
<li><a href="#stats" title="What are my Stats?">Stats</a></li>
<li><a href="#modifiers" title="What are my Modifiers?">Modifiers</a><ul>
<li><a href="#activity-level" title="How do I determine my Activity Level?">Activity Level</a></li>
<li><a href="#goal" title="What should be my Goal calories?">Goal</a></li>
<li><a href="#how-much-protein" title="How much protein should I eat?">How Much Protein?</a></li>
<li><a href="#fat-carb-calorie-split" title="How much fat and carbs should I eat?" >Fat/Carb Calorie Split</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#results" title="What does Results mean?">Results</a><ul>
<li><a href="#bmr" title="What does BMR mean?">BMR</a></li>
<li><a href="#tdee" title="What does TDEE mean?">TDEE</a></li>
<li><a href="#daily-calories-and-macros" title="How many calories should I eat?">Daily Calories and Macros</a></li>
<li><a href="#estimated-weight-loss-per-week" title="How much weight should I lose or gain each week?">Estimated Weight Loss per Week</a></li>
</ul>
<li><a href="#the-leangains-method" title="The Leangains Method">The Leangains Method Calculator</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#age" title="How does age affect my TDEE?">Age</a></li>
<li><a href="#height" title="How does height affect my TDEE?">Height</a></li>
<li><a href="#body-fat" title="How does body fat affect my TDEE?">Body Fat</a></li>
<li><a href="#muscle-mass" title="How does muscle mass affect my TDEE?">Muscle Mass</a></li>
<li><a href="#goal-lg" title="The Leangains Method calorie intake.">Goal (Leangains specific)</a></li>
<li><a href="#steps" title="How many steps per day?">Steps</a></li>
<li><a href="#how-much-protein-lg" title="How much protein should I eat on the Leangains Method?">How much Protein? (Leangains specific)</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</div>

<p>This page breaks down how to use the <a href="/calorie-calculator/" target="_blank" title="Calorie and Macro Calculator">calorie calculator web application</a> to work out your daily calories and macronutrients.</p>
<p>The calculator allows you to forecast your estimated weight change per week based on your calorie deficit/surplus. You can also adjust your protein, fat, and carbohydrate macros as desired. </p>
<p>Your <a href="#bmr" title="What does BMR mean?">BMR</a> and <a href="#tdee" title="What does TDEE mean?">TDEE</a> are displayed for convenience.</p>
<h3 id="stats">Stats</h3>
<p id="start-p">Here you input the following basic personal information:</p>
<ul>
<li>Age (in years)</li>
<li>Weight (in kilograms or pounds)</li>
<li>Height (in centimetres or inches)</li>
<li>Gender (male or female)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="modifiers">Modifiers</h3>
<h4 id="activity-level">Activity Level</h4>
<p>Your <strong>Activity Level</strong> serves as a multiplier on top of your <a title="BMR Defined" target="_blank" href="/blog/calorie-calculator-how-to#bmr"><strong>BMR</strong></a> (Basal Metabolic Rate). The result of this calculation is called your <a title="TDEE Defined" target="_blank" href="/blog/calorie-calculator-how-to#tdee"><strong>TDEE</strong></a> (Total Daily Energy Expenditure).</p>
<p>Think of your BMR as the energy you would need to keep alive if you were in a coma. Energy required for processes like breathing, blood circulation, controlling body temperature, cell growth, etc.</p>
<p>What you care about though, is your TDEE. This is the <strong><em>total amount of energy you need each day to maintain your body weight</em></strong> after you factor in all of your activity.</p>
<p>This is not the same as your BMR, as even the least active among us aren’t lying motionless in bed all day.</p>
<p>The Activity Level modifiers are:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sedentary:</strong> Little or no exercise, office job (1.2&times;)</li>
<li><strong>Lightly Active:</strong> Light daily activity &amp; exercise 1-3 days per week (1.375&times;)</li>
<li><strong>Moderately Active:</strong> Moderate daily activity &amp; exercise 3-5 days per week (1.55&times;)</li>
<li><strong>Very Active:</strong> Physically demanding lifestyle &amp; exercise 6-7 days per week (1.725&times;)</li>
<li><strong>Extremely Active:</strong> Hard daily exercise/sports &amp; physical job (1.9&times;)</li>
</ul>
<p>Be warned: <strong>most people tend to overestimate their activity level</strong>. </p>
<p>This is usually due to them basing their activity level on their number of gym sessions per week. This is not the right way to go about it.</p>
<p>Your activity level is primarily based off of what you do <strong><em>outside</em></strong> the gym. Four 1 hour strength training sessions at the gym each week is less than 2 hours of actual activity. It does <strong><em>not</em></strong> result in a large number of calories burnt.</p>
<p>Conversely, a teacher on her feet for the lions share of the week is most likely <em>“Lightly Active”</em>. The intermittent cardio throughout the day adds up.</p>
<p>If your only activity outside the office is the gym, put yourself down as <em>“Sedentary”</em>. You <em>might</em> be slightly over depending on your intensity and frequency – but more likely you won’t be. You can adjust your estimate based on the first couple week’s progress. </p>
<p>If you think you’re on the line between levels and it could go either way – go with the lower estimate. </p>
<h4 id="goal">Goal</h4>
<p>This dropdown provides an easy way to match your qualitative weight loss/gain goal with a quantitative value. The options are:  </p>
<ul>
<li>Lose Weight (–20%)</li>
<li>Slowly Lose Weight (–10%)</li>
<li>Maintain Weight (0%)</li>
<li>Slowly Gain Weight (+10%)</li>
<li>Gain Weight (+20%)</li>
</ul>
<p>The number in the proceeding brackets specifies the caloric deficit/surplus. For example, (+10%) means that your daily calorie goal will be 10% higher than your <a href="#tdee" target="_blank" title="What does TDEE mean?">TDEE</a>.</p>
<p>Alternatively, you can input a specific calorie goal in the <strong>Calorie Deficit/Surplus</strong> section.</p>
<h4 id="how-much-protein">How Much Protein?</h4>
<p>Here there are 3 standardised options:</p>
<ul id="ul-nm7">
<li>1g per pound</li>
<li>0.82g per pound</li>
<li>1.5g per pound</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>1g per pound</strong> is the standard and recommended option. This provides you with enough protein to facilitate muscle growth <strong><em>with a large margin of error</em></strong>.</p>
<p><strong>0.82g per pound</strong> still provides enough protein to facilitate muscle growth. Think of this as a lower bar for the amount of protein you should be consuming. Although the subject of hot debate, current science points to 0.82g protein/pound being <strong><em>enough</em></strong> protein. </p>
<p>Although it’s <em>unlikely</em> additional protein will result in increased gains, you still may want to consider a higher protein intake as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Protein is a more satiating macronutrient <a title="The effects of high protein diets on thermogenesis, satiety and weight loss: a critical review" target="_blank" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmedhealth/PMH0021577/">[1]</a></li>
<li>A higher protein intake restricts your food choices, forcing you to eat less junk</li>
<li>The TEF (Thermic Effect of Food) means protein is closer to 3.2 kcal per gram, not 4 kcal per gram <a title="A perspective on food energy standards for nutrition labelling." target="_blank" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11299073">[2]</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The above reasoning is why you might even want to consider <strong>1.5g per pound</strong>. </p>
<p>If you’re an expert in going way too far with your cheat meals to the point of ruining your diet – 1.5g per pound is for you.</p>
<h4 id="fat-carb-calorie-split">Fat/Carb Calorie Split</h4>
<p>This is the percentage split (<em>calorie-wise</em>) between fat and carbs <em>after</em> you account for your protein intake.</p>
<p>You have a good amount of leeway in your distribution between carbs and fat. <em><strong>The split between carbs and fat is largely a matter of personal preference</strong></em>. So long as you’re not on the extreme of either side, there is no point stressing about the allocation. 

<p>Some of us feel better with more carbs and less fat, and some of us feel better with more fat and less carbs. In general the more active you are, the more likely you’ll suit a higher carb intake.</p></p>
<p>As a rule of thumb, <strong>you’ll want to consume no less than 0.25g fat per pound, or approximately 0.5g fat per kilogram</strong>. </p>
<p>Although this may seem like a low bar, it can be broken when you’re on a hard cut and hence don’t have that many calories to work with. Getting less than this amount of fat for an elongated period of time can easily lead to dry skin and/or hair. Would not recommend.</p>
<h3 id="results">Results</h3>
<h4 id="bmr">BMR</h4>
<p>Stands for your <strong>Basal Metabolic Rate</strong>.</p>
<p>This is essentially the amount of energy you would need to keep alive if you were in a coma. Energy required for processes like breathing, blood circulation, controlling body temperature, cell growth, etc.</p>
<p>This calculation is based on your Age, Weight, Height, and Gender. It is then multiplied by your <a href="#activity-level" target="_blank" title="How do I determine my Activity Level?"><strong>Activity Level</strong></a> to give your TDEE.</p>
<h4 id="tdee">TDEE</h4>
<p>Stands for your <strong>Total Daily Energy Expenditure</strong>. Also known as your “<em>maintenance calories</em>”.</p>
<p>Your TDEE is the <strong><em>total amount of energy you need each day to maintain your body weight</em></strong> after you factor in all of your activity.</p>
<p>So in an ideal world where you eat your exact TDEE each day, you would maintain the same body weight.</p>
<p>In reality this never happens due to the variance in our daily activity, the exact amount of food we eat, and water weight fluctuations.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, getting a ballpark figure of your TDEE is all you really need to get going. You can track your progress against your estimate and readjust as required.</p>
<h4 id="daily-calories-and-macros">Daily Calories and Macros</h4>
<p>This is final result of all of your input data. It breaks down the Calories, Protein, Fat, and Carbohydrates you should eat each day to reach your physique goals.</p>
<p><strong>Do not stress about small deviations from these numbers</strong>. A &#177;5% difference will not affect your physique. </p>
<p>Why? Each of these numbers have error built in. Even the lower protein intake of 0.82g per pound was based on a 95% confidence interval. </p>
<p><strong>All calorie counters are approximations.</strong> Regardless of how many decimal places worth of carbs MyFitnessPal tells you are in your 160.8 g apple – it’s only an estimate. </p>
<p>Use the calculated values as a solid approximation. Adjust your estimate as required based off of your weight loss/gain during the first few weeks of your diet. If you need help with this, ask. I plan on making a tool to help with this in the near future. </p>
<h4 id="estimated-weight-loss-per-week">Estimated Weight Loss per Week</h4>
<p>This estimate is based on the ~3500 calories in one pound of fat.</p>
<p>E.g. A 500 calorie deficit per day is around 1 pound of fat loss per week.</p>
<p>So what kind of weight gain/loss should you aim for? The below serves as a <strong><em>practical and realistic</em></strong> expectation for a 6 to 12 month program. </p>
<p><strong>Fat Loss with Minimal Muscle Loss</strong></p>
<ul id="ul-nm1">
<li>2 pounds per week in the obese (BMI of 30 or above) </li>
<li>1 pound per week in the overweight (BMI of 25 to 30)</li>
<li>&frac12; pound per week, or less, in guys who are lean and trying to get even leaner </li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Muscle Gain with Minimal Fat Gain</strong></p>
<ul id="ul-nm2">
<li>2 to 3 pounds per month in novices and advanced beginners (those with less than 2 years of consistent strength training)</li>
<li>1 to 2 pounds per month in intermediates (those with 2 to 4 years of consistent training) </li>
<li>&frac12; pound per month in advanced lifters who are close to their genetic ceiling</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s important to note that <strong><em>the first few weeks and months will bring the biggest losses/gains</em></strong>. </p>
<p>For example, it’s common to drop a full 2kg in your first week of cutting – especially if you lowered your carb intake. This is great for motivation, but it’s not a realistic representation of what you should expect long term. </p>
<p>This exaggerated change is primarily due to changes in water weight, as well as the initial shock your body experiences from the abrupt change in calorie intake. </p>
<p><strong>What this means</strong> is that you shouldn’t fret over your weight loss/gains plateauing after the first few weeks. Rather, you should expect it. Don’t let it mess with your motivation.</p>
<h3 id="the-leangains-method">The Leangains Method Calculator</h3>
<p>The following information is specific to the <em>Leangains</em> <a href="/calorie-calculator/?leangains" target="_blank" title="Leangains Calorie and Macro Calculator">calorie and macronutrient calculator</a> (<em>select “Leangains” in the “Diet” dropdown</em>).</p>
<p>This calculator uses the equation recommended by <a title="About: Martin Berkhan" target="_blank" href="https://leangains.com/about-me/">Martin Berkhan</a> in his book <a title="Amazon: The Leangains Method" target="_blank" href="https://amzn.to/2nM1zUH">The Leangains Method</a> to estimate your daily calorie and macronutrient needs.</p>
<p>To use this approach to calculate your <a href="#tdee" target="_blank" title="What does TDEE mean?">TDEE</a>, you multiply your body weight in kilograms by your calculated <em>base value</em>. This base value starts at 28 for men, and 26 for women. </p>
<p>Your base value is modified depending on your <em>Stats</em> – age, height,  body fat, muscle mass, and steps taken each day.</p>
<p>Let’s use our imaginary friend Paul as an example. Paul’s stats are: </p>
<ul>
<li>21 year old male (+0.5)</li>
<li>13% body fat (+0)</li>
<li>180 cm tall (+0)</li>
<li>Muscular (+0.5)</li>
<li>8000 steps per day (+1.0)</li>
</ul>
<p>So Paul’s final base value is &#8594; <em>28 + 0.5 + 0 + 0 + 0.5 + 1.0 = 30</em>. Paul weighs in at 80 kg, so that puts him at: </p>
<blockquote>
<p>80 kg &times; 30 base value = 2400 calorie <a class="no-ul" href="#tdee" title="What does TDEE mean?">TDEE</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Below I explain the specifics of how each factor affects your base value. Note that the <a href="/calorie-calculator/?leangains" target="_blank" title="Leangains Calorie and Macro Calculator">calorie calculator</a> automatically does this math for you. This is just an explanation of the logic behind the calculator, for those interested.</p>
<h4 id="age">Age</h4>
<p>Your age alters your base value in the following way:</p>
<ul id="ul-nm8">
<li>&lt;25 years old: +0.5</li>
<li>25-45 years old: 0</li>
<li>&gt;45 years old: –0.5</li>
</ul>
<p>So an 18 year old man/woman would add 0.5 to their base value.</p>
<h4 id="height">Height</h4>
<p>How your height alters your base value depends on your gender:</p>
<p><strong>For Men</strong> </p>
<ul id="ul-nm9">
<li>&lt;167 cm: –1</li>
<li>167-185 cm: 0</li>
<li>&gt;185 cm: +1</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>167 cm &ap; 5 feet, 5 inches = 65 inches</p>
<p>185 cm &ap; 6 feet, 1 inches = 73 inches</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>For Women</strong> </p>
<ul id="ul-nm10">
<li>&lt;153 cm: –1</li>
<li>153-170 cm: 0</li>
<li>&gt;170 cm: +1</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>153 cm &ap; 5 feet, 0 inches = 60 inches</p>
<p>170 cm &ap; 5 feet, 7 inches = 67 inches</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So a 175 cm tall guy would keep his base value the same, while a 175 cm tall woman would add 1 to her base value.</p>
<h4 id="body-fat">Body Fat</h4>
<p>How your body fat percentage alters your base value depends on your gender:</p>
<p><strong>For Men</strong> </p>
<ul id="ul-nm3">
<li>&lt;10% body fat: +0.5 </li>
<li>11-19% body fat: 0</li>
<li>20-24% body fat: –0.5 </li>
<li>25-29% body fat: –1.5</li>
<li>30-34% body fat: –2.5</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>For Women</strong> </p>
<ul id="ul-nm4">
<li>&lt;18% body fat: +0.5 </li>
<li>19-27% body fat: 0</li>
<li>28-32% body fat: –0.5 </li>
<li>33-37% body fat: –1.5</li>
<li>38-42% body fat: –2.5</li>
</ul>
<p>So a man with 22% body fat would subtract 1.5 from his base value. Whereas a woman with 25% body fat would keep her base value the same.</p>
<h4 id="muscle-mass">Muscle Mass</h4>
<p>Your muscle mass alters your base value in the following way:</p>
<ul id="ul-nm5">
<li>Standard: 0</li>
<li>Muscular: +0.5</li>
<li>Very Muscular: +1</li>
</ul>
<p>Note that <em>Very Muscular</em> is only applicable to males. Martin recommends that those with a Fat-Free Mass Index (FFMI) &gt;22 choose <em>Muscular</em>. For <em>Very Muscular</em>, your FFMI should be &gt;24. </p>
<p>There is no FFMI recommendation for women – women can use <em>Muscular</em> at their own discretion.</p>
<h4 id="goal-lg">Goal (Leangains specific)</h4>
<p>Your goal calories deviate from your <a href="#tdee" target="_blank" title="What does TDEE mean?">TDEE</a> depending on your gender, and whether you’re cutting or bulking. Either way it is a constant number (<em>as opposed to a percentage</em>).</p>
<p>For men, a &#177;500 calorie deficit/surplus depending on whether you’re cutting or bulking. </p>
<p>For women, a &#177;350 calorie deficit/surplus depending on whether you’re cutting or bulking. </p>
<p>This will result in an approximate weight loss/gain of 0.5 kilograms (1.1 pounds) for men, or 0.35 kilograms (0.77 pounds) for women.</p>
<h4 id="steps">Steps</h4>
<p>This is an approximation for the number of steps you take each day. If you want an accurate result, use a pedometer or phone application such as Health (iOS) or Google Fit (Android). </p>
<p>If you’re sedentary for most of your week or are unsure, assume a value of 5000 steps (<em>note that steps less than 6000 have the same activity multiplier</em>). </p>
<p>Your base value is altered as follows: </p>
<ul id="ul-nm6">
<li>&lt;6000 steps: 0 </li>
<li>6000 – 7500 steps: +0.5 </li>
<li>Add another +0.5 for every 1250 step increment above 7500 steps </li>
</ul>
<p>For example, someone taking 9000 steps each day would add 1.5 to their base value.</p>
<h4 id="how-much-protein-lg">How much Protein? (Leangains specific)</h4>
<p><a title="Amazon: The Leangains Method" target="_blank" href="https://amzn.to/2nM1zUH">The Leangains Method</a> recommends getting as close to 60% of your calorie intake from protein as you can. This <strong><em>extremely</em></strong> high protein recommendation is to reap benefits <em>outside</em> of pure muscle building. Namely protein’s high TEF (Thermic Effect of Food), as well as the added difficulty of making poor food choices when you’re eating a high protein diet. </p>
<p>Martin himself finds 55% protein to be his sweet spot. He notes that if you find 60% protein too restrictive then you can drop it down to 50% – which he believes is doable. </p>
<p>If you still think this protein intake is too high, then consider switching the “<em>Diet</em>” dropdown of the <a href="/calorie-calculator/" target="_blank" title="Calorie and Macro Calculator">calorie calculator</a> to “<em>Standard</em>” and selecting a lower protein intake of 0.82g/pound or 1g/pound. This gives you more leeway with your other macros while still provides enough protein for muscle building. More information on protein intakes <a href="#how-much-protein" target="_blank" title="How much Protein?">here</a>.</p>]]></description>
        <pubDate>Mon Nov 05 2018 21:59:21 GMT+0800 (Australian Western Standard Time)</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
