<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home Page</title>
    <link>https://musclehacking.com</link>
    <description>An evidence based approach to fitness and nutrition. Free articles and guides on how to use intermittent fasting to gain muscle, lose fat, and improve your memory and focus.</description>
    <atom:link href="https://musclehacking.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      <item>
        <title>How to use the Calorie Calculator</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<div id="toc_container">
<h4 id="toc-h">Table of Contents</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="#stats">Stats</a></li>
<li><a href="#modifiers">Modifiers</a><ul>
<li><a href="#activity-level">Activity Level</a></li>
<li><a href="#goal">Goal</a></li>
<li><a href="#how-much-protein-">How Much Protein?</a></li>
<li><a href="#fat-carb-calorie-split">Fat/Carb Calorie Split</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#results">Results</a><ul>
<li><a href="#bmr">BMR</a></li>
<li><a href="#tdee">TDEE</a></li>
<li><a href="#daily-calories-and-macros">Daily Calories and Macros</a></li>
<li><a href="#estimated-weight-loss-per-week">Estimated Weight Loss per Week</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</div>

<p><h3 id="stats">Stats</h3></p>
<p id="start-p">Here you input the following basic personal information:</p>
<ul>
<li>Age (in years)</li>
<li>Weight (in kilograms or pounds)</li>
<li>Height (in centimetres or inches)</li>
<li>Gender (male or female)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="modifiers">Modifiers</h3>
<h4 id="activity-level">Activity Level</h4>
<p>Your <strong>Activity Level</strong> serves as a multiplier on top of your <strong>BMR</strong> (Basal Metabolic Rate). The result of this calculation is called your <strong>TDEE</strong> (Total Daily Energy Expenditure).</p>
<p>Think of your BMR as the energy you would need to keep alive if you were in a coma. Energy required for processes like breathing, blood circulation, controlling body temperature, cell growth, etc.</p>
<p>What you care about though, is your TDEE. This is the <strong><em>total amount of energy you need each day to maintain your body weight</em></strong> after you factor in all of your activity.</p>
<p>This is not the same as your BMR, as even the least active among us aren&#39;t lying motionless in bed all day.</p>
<p>These are the Activity Level modifiers:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sedentary:</strong> Little or no exercise, office job (1.2x)</li>
<li><strong>Lightly Active:</strong> Light daily activity &amp; exercise 1-3 days per week (1.375x)</li>
<li><strong>Moderately Active:</strong> Moderate daily activity &amp; exercise 3-5 days per week (1.55x)</li>
<li><strong>Very Active:</strong> Physically demanding lifestyle &amp; exercise 6-7 days per week (1.725x)</li>
<li><strong>Extremely Active:</strong> Hard daily exercise/sports &amp; physical job (1.9x)</li>
</ul>
<p>Be warned: <strong>Most people tend to overestimate their activity level</strong>. </p>
<p>This is usually due to them basing their activity level on their number of gym sessions per week. This is not the right way to go about it.</p>
<p>Your activity level is primarily based off of what you do <strong>outside</strong> the gym. Four 1 hour strength training sessions at the gym each week is less than 2 hours of actual activity. It does not result in a large number of calories burnt.</p>
<p>Conversely, a teacher on her feet for the lions share of the week is most likely <em>“Lightly Active”</em>. The intermittent cardio throughout the day adds up.</p>
<p>If your only activity outside the office is the gym, put yourself down as <em>“Sedentary”</em>. You <em>might</em> be slightly over depending on your intensity and frequency – but more likely you won&#39;t be. You can adjust your estimate based on the first couple week&#39;s progress. </p>
<p>If you think you&#39;re on the line between levels and it could go either way – go with the lower estimate. </p>
<h4 id="goal">Goal</h4>
<p>This dropdown provides an easy way to match your qualitative weight loss/gain goal with a quantitative value. The options are:  </p>
<ul>
<li>Lose Weight (-20%)</li>
<li>Slowly Lose Weight (-10%)</li>
<li>Maintain Weight (0%)</li>
<li>Slowly Gain Weight (+10%)</li>
<li>Gain Weight (+20%)</li>
</ul>
<p>The number in the proceeding brackets specifies the caloric deficit/surplus. For example, (+10%) means that your daily calorie goal will be 10% higher than your TDEE.</p>
<p>Alternatively, you can input a specific calorie goal in the <strong>Calorie Deficit/Surplus</strong> section.</p>
<h4 id="how-much-protein-">How Much Protein?</h4>
<p>Here I have provided 3 standardised options:</p>
<ul>
<li>1g per pound</li>
<li>0.82g per pound</li>
<li>1.5g per pound</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>1g per pound</strong> is the standard and recommended option. This provides you with enough protein to facilitate muscle growth <strong><em>with a large margin of error</em></strong>.</p>
<p><strong>0.82g per pound</strong> still provides enough protein to facilitate muscle growth. Think of this as a lower bar for the amount of protein you should be consuming. Although the subject of hot debate, current science points to 0.82g protein/pound being <strong><em>enough</em></strong> protein. </p>
<p>Although it&#39;s <em>unlikely</em> additional protein will result in increased gains, you still may want to consider a higher protein intake as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Protein is a more satiating macronutrient <a title="The effects of high protein diets on thermogenesis, satiety and weight loss: a critical review" target="_blank" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmedhealth/PMH0021577/">[1]</a></li>
<li>A higher protein intake restricts your food choices, forcing you to eat less junk</li>
<li>The TEF (Thermic Effect of Food) means protein is closer to 3.2 kcal per gram, not 4 kcal per gram <a title="A perspective on food energy standards for nutrition labelling." target="_blank" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11299073">[2]</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The above reasoning is why you might even want to consider <strong>1.5g per pound</strong>. </p>
<p>If you&#39;re an expert in going way too far with your cheat meals to the point of ruining your diet – 1.5g per pound is for you.</p>
<h4 id="fat-carb-calorie-split">Fat/Carb Calorie Split</h4>
<p>This is the <strong>percentage split between fat and carbs <em>after</em> you account for your protein intake</strong>. </p>
<p>You have a good amount of leeway in your distribution between carbs and fat. It&#39;s largely a matter of personal preference. Some of us feel better with more carbs and less fat, and some of us feel better with more fat and less carbs. Generally the more active you are, the better you&#39;ll feel on a higher level of carbs.</p>
<p>As a rule of thumb, <strong>you&#39;ll want to consume no less than 0.25g fat per pound, or approximately 0.5g fat per kilogram</strong>. </p>
<p>Although this may seem like a low bar, it can still be broken when you&#39;re on a hard cut and you don&#39;t have that many calories to work with. Getting less than this amount of fat for an elongated period of time can easily lead to dry skin and/or hair. Would not recommend.</p>
<h3 id="results">Results</h3>
<h4 id="bmr">BMR</h4>
<p>Stands for your <strong>Basal Metabolic Rate</strong>. </p>
<p>Essentially the amount of energy you would need to keep alive if you were in a coma. Energy required for processes like breathing, blood circulation, controlling body temperature, cell growth, etc.</p>
<p>This is calculated via your Age, Weight, Height, and Gender. It is then multiplied by your <strong>Activity Level</strong> to give your TDEE.</p>
<h4 id="tdee">TDEE</h4>
<p>Stands for your <strong>Total Daily Energy Expenditure</strong>. Also known as your “<em>maintenance calories</em>”. </p>
<p>This is the <strong><em>total amount of energy you need each day to maintain your body weight</em></strong> after you factor in all of your activity.</p>
<p>So in an ideal world where you eat your exact TDEE each day, you would maintain the same body weight.</p>
<p>In reality this never happens due to the variance in our daily activity, the exact amount of food we eat, and water weight fluctuations.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, getting a ballpark figure of your TDEE is all you really need to get going. You can track your progress against your estimate and readjust as required.</p>
<h4 id="daily-calories-and-macros">Daily Calories and Macros</h4>
<p>This is final result of all of your input data. It breaks down the Calories, Protein, Fat, and Carbohydrates you should eat each day to reach your physique goals.</p>
<p><strong>Do not stress about small deviations from these numbers</strong>. A &#177;5% difference will not affect your physique. </p>
<p>Why? Each of these numbers have error built in. Even the lower protein intake of 0.82g per pound was based on a 95% confidence interval. </p>
<p><strong>All calorie counters are approximations.</strong> Regardless of how many decimal places worth of carbs MyFitnessPal tells you are in your 160.8 g apple – it&#39;s only an estimate. </p>
<p>Use the calculated values as a solid approximation. Adjust your estimate as required based off of your weight loss/gain during the first few weeks of your diet. If you need help with this, ask. I plan on making a tool to help with this in the near future. </p>
<h4 id="estimated-weight-loss-per-week">Estimated Weight Loss per Week</h4>
<p>This estimate is based on the ~3500 calories in one pound of fat.</p>
<p>E.g. A 500 calorie deficit per day is around 1 pound of fat loss per week.</p>
<p>So what kind of weight gain/loss should you aim for? The below serves as a <strong><em>practical and realistic</em></strong> expectation for a 6 to 12 month program. </p>
<p><strong>Fat Loss with Minimal Muscle Loss</strong></p>
<ul id="ul-nm1">
<li>2 pounds per week in the obese (BMI of 30 or above) </li>
<li>1 pound per week in the overweight (BMI of 25 to 30)</li>
<li>&frac12; pound per week, or less, in guys who are lean and trying to get even leaner </li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Muscle Gain with Minimal Fat Gain</strong></p>
<ul id="ul-nm2">
<li>2 to 3 pounds per month in novices and advanced beginners (those with less than 2 years of consistent strength training)</li>
<li>1 to 2 pounds per month in intermediates (those with 2 to 4 years of consistent training) </li>
<li>&frac12; pound per month in advanced lifters who are close to their genetic ceiling</li>
</ul>
<p>It&#39;s important to note that <strong><em>the first few weeks and months will bring the biggest losses/gains</em></strong>. </p>
<p>For example, it&#39;s common to drop a full 2kg in your first week of cutting – especially if you lowered your carb intake. This is great for motivation, but it&#39;s not a realistic representation of what you should expect long term. </p>
<p>This exaggerated change is primarily due to changes in water weight, as well as the initial shock your body experiences from the adrupt change in calorie intake. </p>
<p><strong>What this means</strong> is that you shouldn&#39;t fret over your weight loss/gains plateauing after the first few weeks. Rather, you should expect it. Don&#39;t let it mess with your motivation.</p>
<p>That&#39;s it for this how-to guide. Hit me up if you have any further questions. </p>
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Fri Jun 08 2018 15:56:38 GMT+0800 (AWST)</pubDate>
        <link>https://musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>A Healthy, Organic, Naturally Flavoured Post</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>They’re a great way for a company to either sincerely inform you of the positive aspects of their product – <strong>or completely mislead you into making you believe that what you’re buying is somehow <em>‘good for you’</em></strong>. This can lead to problems if you’re not aware of exactly what a claim means.</p>
<p>Let’s look at a typical example:</p>
<ul>
<li>Stacey has just started a new diet, and is browsing her local supermarket</li>
<li>Stacey buys a pack of nut bars that claim to be a <em>“healthy snack”</em></li>
<li>Every time Stacey gets hungry between meals, she nibbles on a nut bar</li>
<li>2 weeks and a couple boxes later, Stacey is 2 pounds heavier</li>
</ul>
<p>This can be a very frustrating experience for Stacey. She was under the impression that replacing her favourite chocolate with this <em>“healthy snack”</em> would help her lose weight. So what gives?</p>
<p>Stacey’s weight loss woes can be attributed to clever marketing blended with a lack consumer understanding. Like many people, Stacey has associated the word <em>“healthy”</em> to <em>“low calorie”</em>.  <strong><em>But ”healthy” and “low calorie” do not mean the same thing.</em></strong>  </p>
<p>Something is usually deemed <em>“healthy”</em> (or <em>”good for you”</em>) due to it having a lot of <a href="https://www.nal.usda.gov/fnic/vitamins-and-minerals" target="_blank" title="Micronutrient defined">micronutrients</a> (i.e. vitamins &amp; minerals), regardless of its <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/public-health-nutrition/article/macronutrients-as-sources-of-food-energy/DDF89DE14E92D39D56A45FBAA3F00A55 " target="_blank" title="Macronutrient defined">macronutrient</a> content. Macronutrients are fat, protein and carbohydrates. They define the calorie content of your food,  and subsequently the success of your weight loss efforts.</p>
<p><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new3">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/VegetaResized-min.jpg" alt="Paleo cookies don't help">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> So you’re telling me I ate all those horrible paleo cookies for nothing? </p></p>
<p>If Stacey were brave enough to flip the box and read the nutrition label, she would find that these <em>“healthy”</em> nut bars actually have quite a lot of fat in them. Although many would argue these to be <em>“healthy fats”</em>, this does not relieve them of their high calorie content. Not ideal for dieting, as they can easily lead to unwanted weight gain.</p>
<p>Note that the supplier hasn’t actually lied about their product. Nuts are <em>“healthy”</em>, but something can be <em>healthy</em> without requiring it to be low in calories – nuts being a prime example. The conflation of these characteristics can lead people to believe that a product is something it’s not.</p>
<p><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/Walnuts&Choc.jpg" alt="Calories in Chocolate vs. Walnuts">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Walnuts actually contain more calories per gram than chocolate, with around ~65 calories/10g, while chocolate is ~50-60 calories/10g [depending on the type and % of cacao] <a title="Calories in Walnuts" target="_blank" href="https://ndb.nal.usda.gov/ndb/foods/show/12155?fgcd=&manu=&format=&count=&max=25&offset=&sort=default&order=asc&qlookup=walnut&ds=SR&qt=&qp=&qa=&qn=&q=&ing=">[1]</a>
<a title="Calories in Chocolate" target="_blank" href="https://ndb.nal.usda.gov/ndb/foods/show/19081?man=&lfacet=&count=&max=25&qlookup=chocolate&offset=&sort=default&format=Abridged&reportfmt=other&rptfrm=&ndbno=&nutrient1=&nutrient2=&nutrient3=&subset=&totCount=&measureby=&Qv=1&Q333352=1&Q333353=1&Qv=10&Q333352=1&Q333353=1">[2]</a></p> </p>
<p>Now don’t get me wrong; I’m not hating on nut bars. I’m merely using them as an example to illustrate my point. I could just as easily have talked about candy that boasts about having <em>“No Artificial Colours or Flavours”</em> or being <em>“99% Fat Free”</em>. The number of people who read these labels and think <em>“These are good for me”</em> is concerning. Once familiar with this type of advertising, you’ll instead instantly conclude: <em>“Made with 100% Sugar”</em>.</p>
<p>I’m not saying that sugar is the devil and you should avoid it at all costs – because it definitely isn’t and you definitely shouldn’t. But when you indulge on a sweet treat it’s important to be aware that it is just that: a sweet treat. Otherwise there’ll be no guilt stopping you from heading down to your local burger joint and ordering a big mac and fries for round 2. I mean, why not - you’ve eaten so well today!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“But when you indulge on a sweet treat make sure you’re mentally aware that it is just that: a sweet treat.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You can easily see how these kind of eatings habits can lead to a calorie surplus and unwanted weight gain.</p>
<p><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new2">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/majin-buu.gif" alt="Eating cake">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Don’t worry – it’s Gluten Free </p></p>
<p>I don’t think this is a marketing problem. If a candy company wants to accurately label its product as having <em>“No Artificial Colours or Flavours”</em>, they should be able to. That way those looking to buy candy without artificial colours or flavours will be able to easily identify what products they can choose from.</p>
<p>To fix this issue long term, we need to bridge the gap in consumer knowledge. When a consumer reads <em>“No Artificial Colours or Flavours”</em> on a pack of candy, they should establish that it is likely that the product is almost entirely made of sugar. Although it would be convenient, I think it’s unrealistic to expect a company to actively market such information. Until crooked teeth become fashionable, we probably won’t see:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;No artificial colours or flavours. Fuck tonnes of sugar&quot;</p>
<p>— Nestl&eacute;  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>Jokes aside, the asymmetric information between suppliers and consumers in the food industry is a serious problem. Although the average consumer is better at reading a label than they used to be, that doesn’t say much. I’ve known people who thought a product was <em>“healthy”</em> purely because it carried the label <em>“Low in salt!”</em> - which is what I imagine a marketer’s wet dream to be like.</p>
<p><em>“Where are you going with this?”</em>. Good question. The issue has become incredibly broad, and I wanted to touch on a multitude of other things. Such as high sugar cereals that justify themselves being good for kids solely due to the vitamins &amp; minerals they inject into the end of the ingredients. Or <em>“No Added Cane Sugar!”</em> drinks that graciously replace the cane sugar with fruit sugar (fructose). And not to forget the old <em>“Heart Foundation Tick of Approval”</em> = this product is good for me. With all these options available to mislead the uninformed consumer, it’s no wonder that people find proper nutrition to be so disheartenedly confusing.</p>
<p>So lets shed some light on some of the most common and pernicious marketing techniques.
The table below outlines:</p>
<ol>
<li>Common food labels</li>
<li>What they’re generally interpreted to mean</li>
<li>What they really mean</li>
<li>What to keep in mind when you read them (red flags)</li>
</ol>
<p>I’ve also mentioned the typical foods you’ll see these labels slapped onto. Stacey’s love handles never stood a chance.</p>
<p><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new4">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/ChiChiShopping-min.jpg" alt="Eating Healthy">
</picture><p class ="figurecap fig-centre"> Post-reading this article, you can see Stacey has made some solid food choices </p>
<br></p>
<p><div class="table-responsive">
  <table class="table">
    <thead class="thead-dark">
      <tr>
        <th id="th-1" scope="col" style="width: 20%; min-width: 125px;">Label</th>
        <th id="th-2" scope="col" style="width: 25%; min-width: 150px;">What Stacey Thinks It Means</th>
        <th id="th-3" scope="col" style="width: 25%; min-width: 180px; ">What It Really Means</th>
        <th id="th-4" scope="col" style="width: 30%; min-width: 200px;">What To Look Out For</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/table1.jpg" alt="Gluten Free">
        </picture></th>
        <td>Somehow it has become common belief that anything gluten free is healthy.</td>
        <td>It lacks gluten, a protein found in wheat. ~1% of the population are unable to digest gluten.</td>
        <td>Everything. This is a red flag. Despite what some may tell you, a product being gluten free does not provide any information about its nutritional value.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/table2.jpg" alt="99% Fat Free">
        </picture></th>
        <td>Anything free of fat is good for me and/or will help me lose fat.</td>
        <td>The product has less than 1% of its calories derived from fat.</td>
        <td>High sugar content. It’s a very common label among lolly companies, which is ridiculous since nearly all candy is inherently 99% Fat Free.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/table3.jpg" alt="Low in Salt">
        </picture></th>
        <td>Salt is the demon child of its sugar daddy. Thus, anything low in salt is good right?</td>
        <td>There isn’t much salt. That’s it. That’s all it means.</td>
        <td>Everything. A product bragging about this is a red flag.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/table4.jpg" alt="All Natural Ingredients">
        </picture></th>
        <td>Anything natural is good for me.</td>
        <td>Natural is defined as <em>“something that exists in nature”</em>. For reference, Arsenic is also 100% natural (please don’t eat arsenic).</td>
        <td>Its fat and sugar content, especially the latter. Products that use a lot of sugar love this label.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/table5.jpg" alt="No Added Sugar">
        </picture></th>
        <td>1) No added sugar is the same as having no sugar at all
  2) It’s good for me, because sugar is always bad and I should avoid it.</td>
        <td>They haven’t added any sugar to their product. Note that a product can have a very high sugar content and still have no added sugar.</td>
        <td>Its fat, sugar, and calorie content. A stick of butter has no added sugar, but you wouldn’t assume it’s healthy just because I slapped that label on it would you?</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/table6.jpg" alt="">
        </picture></th>
        <td>Vegans are typically healthy and skinny. So if vegans eat it, it must be good.</td>
        <td>No animal or animal products were used or harmed in the creation of said product.</td>
        <td>The calorie content. These products usually sit at the extremes, being either very low calorie (coconut water ice-cream) or very high calorie (nut-related products).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/table7.jpg" alt="Vegan Friendly">
        </picture></th>
        <td>In the words of a friend “<em>It means it’s clean</em>”.</td>
        <td>“<em>Organic agriculture produces products using methods that preserve the environment and avoid most synthetic materials, such as pesticides and antibiotics</em>”.</td>
        <td>Being good for the environment is great, but it is not a good indicator of its nutritional value.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/table8.jpg" alt="">
        </picture></th>
        <td>My ancestors were nutrition experts. Thus anything Paleo MUST be healthy.</td>
        <td>Unnecessary restrictions on what you can and can’t eat (<a class="anchor"  href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M5kx9FrIhJU" target="_blank" title="Paleo Cream Puffs" ><em>why can’t I have my peanuts and coffee again?</em></a>).</td>
        <td>Everything. Although more specifically many paleo foods can be deceptively high in calories.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/table9.jpg" alt="Organic Ingredients">
        </picture></th>
        <td>The Heart Foundation said it’s good for my heart. Hence it must be good for me.</td>
        <td>“<em>…varieties that are lower in saturated fat, trans fat, salt, and kilojoules, and contain ingredients and nutrients that are better for you, like fibre, calcium, whole grains and vegetables</em>” - The Heart Foundation  </td>
        <td>The Heart Foundation is glued to the idea that fat is bad for the heart and sugar is a non-issue. As such, many foods with extremely high sugar levels have this tick.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th scope="row"><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--square">
          <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/table10.jpg" alt="Paleo Friendly">
        </picture></th>
        <td>I’m not sure what a whole grain is but it sure sounds nutritious.</td>
        <td>The grain has the bran, the endosperm, and the germ in tact. </td>
        <td>Having all three parts of the grain does not make a product healthy and/or low calorie.</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</div>
<br>
Hopefully this will help you out on your next trip to the supermarket – or at the very least give you a good laugh. The first time I started flipping around boxes and reading the ingredients and nutritional breakdown of so-called <em>“healthy foods”</em>, I was in the store for well over an hour in awe.</p>
<p>If a lot of what you’ve just read is news to you – you have been warned.</p>
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Fri Jun 08 2018 15:56:38 GMT+0800 (AWST)</pubDate>
        <link>https://musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>What is Intermittent Fasting?</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p><strong>&quot;Don’t forget to eat your breakfast Jimmy – it’s the most important meal of the day!</strong>
<br><br>
<strong>&quot;...fuck off Mum”</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Whoa, bit harsh there Jimmy. While it&#39;s true that you don’t need to eat breakfast in the mornings, Mom had good intentions.</p>
<p>After all, it&#39;s all she&#39;s ever known.</p>
<p>Anyone growing up in the United States from the 1960s to the 1980s who watched Saturday morning cartoons saw countless advertisements that emphasised the importance of breakfast.</p>
<p>Animated characters and jingles of all sorts taught kids not to head off to school before eating something. Otherwise they wouldn&#39;t have any <em>energy</em>. They wouldn&#39;t be able to <em>focus</em>. What they needed, was a <strong><em>&quot;balanced breakfast&quot;</em></strong>.</p>
<p><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new7">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/cheeriosbulk.jpg" alt="Cheerios Commercial">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> General Mill&#39;s Cheerios: &quot;<em>Energy O&#39;s that help you grow</em>&quot; </p></p>
<p>According to the TV a <em>&quot;balanced breakfast&quot;</em> may include: Cheerios, Cocoa Puffs, Lucky Charms, Trix, and/or Frosted Flakes. These cereals fought to get into the cupboards of as many American families as possible. A child&#39;s eating habits depended on which cereal had the coolest cartoon character, or the catchiest jingle.</p>
<p>No matter which cereal won the battle, <strong>breakfast won the war</strong>. It was a brutally effective strategy. How often have you heard that <strong><em>&quot;Breakfast is the most important meal of the day&quot;</em></strong>? It&#39;s parroted to us so often that it&#39;s almost blasphemous to say otherwise.</p>
<p>Well, I was never one for Sunday school. Nor am I a fan of breakfast. As it turns out, <strong><em>cereal companies may have had ulterior motives</em></strong> when they asserted breakfast to be the king of all meals. Who would have thought?</p>
<p>Intermittent fasting points out that the emperor isn’t wearing any clothes.</p>
<p><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new6">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/bowladay2.jpg" alt="Apple Jacks Commercial">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Kellog&#39;s Apple Jacks: <em>&quot;A bowl a day gives you energy to play&quot;</em> </p></p>
<p>When you intermittently fast, you confine your eating to a pre-defined period of the day. This generally involves <strong>skipping your morning breakfast</strong>.</p>
<h3>Why?</h3><p>Well, why do you eat when you eat right now? Have you ever actually thought about it? You probably adopted the eating habits of your parents, who adopted the eating habits of their parents. But don’t blame Nanna – she was just following everyone else.</p>
<p>People tend to reinforce each other&#39;s beliefs in self-perpetuating loops. Each round of mutual confirmation tightens our beliefs further. Until we have little choice but to believe what everyone else believes: <em>&quot;Breakfast is the most important meal of the day&quot;</em>. </p>
<p>So have we always eaten in the mornings? Did we evolve with an around-the-clock buffet, eating 5+ times per day? </p>
<p>No. We evolved with elongated periods of fasting and feeding. Food was eaten when it was available. If you didn&#39;t kill anything until 2pm, then you fasted until 2pm.</p>
<p>But hold on – <strong>how did we manage to kill anything without any <em>energy</em> or <em>focus?</em></strong> </p>
<p>From a survival perspective, a lack of food would warrant an increased level of concentration. We had better stay focused if we want to catch our next meal.</p>
<p>And this is exactly what you experience while fasting.</p>
<p><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new10">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/cavemanbreakfast-min.jpg" alt="Caveman breakfast">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> <em>Fuck sake Mum, I said I wanted Cheerios</em> </p></p>
<p>I know, I know:</p>
<p><em><strong>&quot;But every time I skip breakfast I’m starving – I can&#39;t concentrate!”</strong></em></p>
<p>I was the exact same. Worse than that – I would eat a big breakfast and be famished by 11am. <strong>Before I skipped breakfast, I tried everything to make it more satiating.</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>I was told oats were filling, so I ate oats in the mornings. <strong>Hungry at 11am.</strong></li>
<li>I was told fruit was filling, so I added fruit to my oats. <strong>Hungry at 11am.</strong></li>
<li>I was told protein was filling, so I added an egg to my oats (this tastes way better than it sounds). <strong>Hungry at 11am.</strong></li>
<li>I was told almonds were filling... you see the trend?</li>
</ul>
<p><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new5">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/oats-other-min.jpg" alt="Oats for breakfast">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Delicious breakfast. Still hungry at 11am. </p>    </p>
<p>I stumbled upon intermittent fasting in search of a better morning. I was sick of the time lost making and eating breakfast. I was sick of the ups and downs in concentration. And most of all, <strong><em>I was sick of the hunger pangs.</em></strong></p>
<p>So when I heard that I could lose weight, save time, and increase my concentration via skipping breakfast, I was as skeptical as you. But. I was willing to give it a shot, <strong>since my current eating habits <em>clearly</em> weren’t working.</strong></p>
<blockquote>
<p>“...when I heard that I could lose weight, save time, and increase my concentration via skipping breakfast, I was as skeptical as you.”    </p>
</blockquote>
<p>And oh boy was I hungry... for the first week. That’s roughly how long it will take for your hunger hormones to adjust to your new eating routine. After that, pure bliss. Now <strong>I enjoy more <em>time</em>, more <em>focus</em>, but <em>no more hunger.</em></strong></p>
<p>I’ve been intermittent fasting for over 4 years now, and I can’t see myself turning back. It’s amazing what a huge difference such a simple change can make.</p>
<h3>How?</h3><p>Intermittent fasting defines your day into two periods. A fasting period, and a feeding period. The latter is also referred to as an “<em>eating window”</em>.</p>
<p>No one is eating around the clock, so everyone is already fasting and feeding naturally. But. We aren’t doing it intentionally, which results in too large an eating window.</p>
<p>Although we <em>generally</em> stop eating at around 9pm, if your stomach growls at 11pm you might pop back into the kitchen for a snack.</p>
<p>You <em>usually</em> eat breakfast at 8am, but you’re starving this morning. So you have it a little earlier at 7am.</p>
<p>So we fast from our last scoop of ice cream at night to our first spoonful of cereal in the morning. This results in most people fasting for less than 12 hours. Not ideal.</p>
<p><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new9">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/homer2-min.jpg" alt="Eating at night">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> Just a nibble? </p></p>
<p>There are many different fasting and feeding routines. One popular and effective routine is an eating window from 12pm to 8pm each day (<em>made popular as the <a href="http://leangains.com/" target="_blank" title="leangains.com">leangains</a> routine</em>).</p>
<p>This means that you don’t start consuming solid or liquid calories until 12pm, and you stop no later than 8pm.</p>
<p>This has myriad benefits compared to some alternate routines.</p>
<p>Firstly, the consistent eating window <strong>regulates your hunger hormones</strong>. The reason your stomach rumbles at 8am is because your body is used to eating at 8am. It’s expecting food.</p>
<p>At your regular breakfast time, your body releases Ghrelin (<em>a primary hunger hormone</em>) and widens your stomach in preparation for food. <strong><em>This makes you hungry</em></strong>.</p>
<p>Now if you start eating at 12pm, your body adapts to your new eating habits. Your hunger will now develop at 12pm, not 8am. And just like that: <strong>no more morning hunger.</strong></p>
<p>By the same token, you’ll no longer be tempted to snack at night. If you consistently cut off your eating by 8pm, your body will no longer expect food past 8pm.</p>
<p><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--2">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/homer7-min.jpg" alt="Midnight snacks">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> No more midnight snacks </p></p>
<p>It gets better. <strong><em>When you have less time to eat, you eat less.</em></strong> </p>
<p>You might suspect that you’ll binge after not eating for so long. But most people find that they naturally eat less. This is especially true if you’re eating satiating foods.  <strong>There just isn&#39;t enough time for your fullness to subside</strong>. </p>
<p>Granted you can still go into a calorie surplus if you go overboard.  If you only eat high calorie junk then you will still gain weight. But even then, it’s harder to do. </p>
<p>The fixed eating window is a one-two punch on weight loss. The left punch stops you snacking throughout the day. The right punch doesn’t give you time to regain your hunger. Before you know it, your hunger is knocked out cold. Weight loss becomes a breeze.</p>
<p><picture class="intrinsic intrinsic--new11">
  <img class="intrinsic-item" src="/img/strawberrysmiggles2-min.jpg" alt="Strawberry smiggles">
</picture><p class ="figurecap"> No longer tempted by strawberry smiggles </p></p>
<p>So intermittent fasting helps you:</p>
<ul>
<li>Get rid of your morning hunger</li>
<li>Improve your concentration</li>
<li>Save time</li>
<li>Eat less</li>
</ul>
<p>There is also emerging evidence that fasting can help you live longer (<em>link</em>). That will be explored more in another post. </p>
<p>If you’re currently fit, healthy, have plenty of spare time, and have no trouble staying focused, then keep on doing what you’re doing. But if you want to improve in any of these areas, then consider intermittent fasting. </p>
<p>Got an intermittent fasting related question? Check out the FAQ. Otherwise, drop me a comment below. </p>
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Fri Jun 08 2018 15:56:38 GMT+0800 (AWST)</pubDate>
        <link>https://musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://musclehacking.com/blog/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
